<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The sword doubled to cut off both the righteous and the wicked; drawn forth in two following discourses, by William Erberie.</title>
            <author>Erbery, William, 1604-1654.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 143KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 35 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A84079</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865966</idno>
  <idno type="VID">118224</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240911824</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing E3238</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E686_15</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206871</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865966</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99865966e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A84079)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 118224)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 106:E686[15])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The sword doubled to cut off both the righteous and the wicked; drawn forth in two following discourses, by William Erberie.</title>
                  <author>Erbery, William, 1604-1654.</author>
                  <author>Erbery, William, 1604-1654. Grand oppressor, or, the terror of tithes.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 64 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by G.D. for Giles Calvert, and are to be sold at the sign of the Black Spread-Eagle at the West End of Pauls,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1652 [i.e. 1653?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reissue (?) of Erberie's "The grand oppressor, or, the terror of tithes; first felt, and now confest .. 1652" with the added titlepage from that item positioned as the title page and a new added title replacing it: "A scourge for the Assyrian, the great oppressor .. 1652".</note>
                  <note>Thomason recieved this copy in 1653. A reissue?.</note>
                  <note>In two parts, each with separate dated titlepage; pagination and register are continuous. Pt. 1 titlepage reads: "The grand oppressor, or, the terror of tithes"; Pt. 2 titlepage reads: "A scourge for the Assyrian, the great oppressor.".</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Feb: 14".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Tithes --  Great Britain --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  Church history --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  Church history --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:118224:1"/>
            <p>THE Sword Doubled To cut off both the RIGHTEOUS AND THE WICKED;</p>
            <p>Drawn forth in two following Discourses, By WILLIAM ERBERIE.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>ISAIAH 31.4.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Thus hath the Lord spoken unto me, like as the Lyon and the young Lion roaring on his prey, when a multitude of Shepherds is called forth against him, he will not be afraid of their voyce, nor abase himself for the noise of them; So shall the Lord of Hosts come down to fight for mount Zion, and for the hill thereof.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>G. D.</hi> for <hi>Giles Calvert,</hi> and are to be sold at the Sign of the Black Spread-Eagle at the West End of <hi>Pauls,</hi> 1652.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:118224:2"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:118224:2"/>
                  <p>THE Grand Oppressor, Or, The Terror of TITHES; First FELT, and now CONFEST:</p>
                  <p>By WILLIAM ERBERIE.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>G. D.</hi> for <hi>Giles Calvert,</hi> and are to be sold at the Sign of the Black Spread-Eagle at the West End of <hi>Pauls,</hi> 1652.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="letter">
                  <pb facs="tcp:118224:3"/>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:118224:3"/>
                  <head>The Sum of a Letter written to one of the Commissioners in <hi>South-Wales, Aprill</hi> 19. 1652.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>OU willed me to write unto you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the hundred pound which you were pleased to promise present paiment of, if your Treasury were not empty:</p>
                  <p>But since I saw you last, the Lord ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared so terribly unto me, that (ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving <hi>torn the caul of my heart</hi>) he discovered the hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrisie and covetousnesse that lay hid,
<note place="margin">Hos. 13.8.</note> and close co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered in my flesh.</p>
                  <p>That which brought it forth (next to the eternal spirit and everlasting burnings within me) was a bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sinesse of Tithes, which I took at first from your hands as a maintenance allowed me by the Lord, in you and the rest of the honourable Commissioners, who in much love appointed this as a portion for my poor Family, and as a reward for my former services and sufferings for the State, and the Saints in <hi>Wales.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Which undeserved favour (as I thankfully acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge) so did I quietly possesse the same in silence and quietness of mind, till the Lord God Almighty began to <hi>roar like a man of War,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Isai. 42.13, 14</note>
                     <hi>and to cry like a woman in tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel</hi> within me, bringing forth himself in that I shall now declare unto you, and to the Churches in <hi>Wales.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I told you Sir in private, that in my late publique
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:118224:4"/>Teachings I was carried forth contrary to the inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of my own Spirit, willing rather to sit still in silence, and spiritual retirements with my God, wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for his glorious appearance with power in all his people.</p>
                  <p>But so it was, that by a speciall providence I came a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad to the people, whom I acquainted that to my present apprehension, I was not certain that I had any call from God or man, or from my self, but meerly by a strong hand, I know not how, I was thrust forth into the Harvest, where I was immediatly met with the noyse of Tythes in this manner:</p>
                  <p>The first Scripture I opened, not to preach, but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to expound, (according to the Teaching of God in mee) was <hi>Isaiah</hi> 61.1, 2.</p>
                  <p>There I saw and said, that God in Christ had glad tidings to speak, and great things to doe (in these last dayes also) for three sorts of people; for the poor, for the oppressed, and for the Prisoner.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The meek</hi> thats the <hi>poor,</hi> as Christ interprets <hi>Luke</hi> 4.18. <hi>the broken hearted,</hi> thats the <hi>oppressed,</hi> as every Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty can testifie, and the <hi>opening of the prison doors to them that are bound, is good tydings for the Prisoner.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This day</hi> (saith Christ) <hi>is this Scripture fulfilled in your eares;</hi> and this have we heard and seen in our dayes, God so appearing in the present powers, that 'twas hoped this was <hi>the acceptable year of the Lord,</hi> for the people of the Land to look for their long expected and promised liberty to the Captives, who, by an Act of Justice and Mercy from the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> are set free from their severall Prisons, (yea, from for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rain captivity in part) as the first fruits of that follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Redemption which the oppressed, and the Poor of the Nation doe likewise hope for.</p>
                  <p>But before I heard of that News, I had formed my matter in this Method;
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>March</hi> 7.</note> the first moneth of the year I began to speak for the poor from these Scriptures
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:118224:4"/>on severall Sundayes, <hi>Isa.</hi> 61.1, 2. and 14.32. <hi>Zeph.</hi> 3.12. <hi>Psal.</hi> 72.4.</p>
                  <p>With this last I began the second moneth for the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed, <hi>Psal.</hi> 72.4.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Aprill</hi> 4. <hi>May</hi> 2. to 30</note> as afterward I ended the third moneth with the Prisoner, from <hi>Isai.</hi> 42.6, 7, and 49, 8, 9. <hi>Zach.</hi> 9.11, 12. but before that I spake for the oppressed, from <hi>Psal.</hi> 72. <hi>v.</hi> 1.4. that when <hi>the King and his Son should come to raign, he would break in pieces the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressor,</hi> oppression must cease, and the oppressed must have ease.</p>
                  <p>The next first day of the week, I spake from <hi>v.</hi> 12, 13, 14. That <hi>the bloud</hi> of poor <hi>oppressed men is most pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious in the eyes of God,</hi> for he <hi>eyes them</hi> and all their op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressors as another Prophet phraseth it, <hi>Zach.</hi> 9.9.</p>
                  <p>Upon this God began (as I said before) to roar in my Spirit, and I to hear nothing within me but the cry of the oppressed, 'twas far (me thought) from my tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to tread on a worm, or to oppresse the poorest creature in the world, but still 'twas told me both wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king and sleeping that God would <hi>break in pieces the oppressor,</hi> and that the <hi>bloud</hi> of the poor was <hi>precious in his sight.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Then the oppression of Tithes came to my eares, and the cry of the oppressed filled my heart, telling me, That I and my children fed on their flesh, that we drunk their bloud, and lived softly on their hard labour and sweat.</p>
                  <p>All the Petitions against Tithes were presently pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented and spread before me by God, who asked, Is it not the gain of oppression that thou and thine live on?</p>
                  <p>Truly Sir, there was never a day went over my head, but I heard something of him from God, and from men also, who, not knowing the working and wrath that was within, did continually hit me in the teeth with something of Tithes.</p>
                  <p>One came to my Chamber, a worthy Gentleman from
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:118224:5"/>
                     <hi>England,</hi> complaining of the Commissioners of <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth</hi>-shire, who (as he came along) had a meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at Christchurch, to take a more strict account of each mans Tithes, and that he met with many poor country men in the way crying out of their oppression, and that (as they said) by the people of God.</p>
                  <p>Another day an honest man of our Country, comes in and tells me, he had formerly taken a good bargain of Tithes from the Commissioners or <hi>Glamorgan</hi>-shire, but he had no rest in his spirit from the time he farmed it from them, but was continually tormented till he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered it up, which he did (as he said) very quickly, else he thought in his heart he had run starke mad out of his wits.</p>
                  <p>And truly Sir 'twas so with me in this, though I have been <hi>afflicted from my youth, and suffered the terrors of the Lord to distraction,</hi> yet (for the time) I was never so distracted, confounded, and filled with feares in all my former temptations, as in this of Tithes.</p>
                  <p>And yet this trouble was not like those legall terrors I suffered of old, but it was like fire in my bones, which I beleeve is the eternall Spirit, and everlasting burnings, which will shortly break forth upon all the oppressors of the land, to burn up their flesh, fulnesse, and those fair buildings which they have raised on the ruines of others, enriching themselves in the Nations poverty.</p>
                  <p>The fire that was within me had new fuell cast there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which to my feeling increased to feircer flames, for every day I opened my Bible to read (the remembrance of Tithes coming still to my mind) the first line that darted in mine eyes, was alwayes something against Oppression, as <hi>Isay</hi> 5.7, 8. <hi>Micah</hi> 2.2, 3, 8, 9, 10. <hi>ver.</hi> Again, <hi>Isaiah</hi> 9.16, 17, 18, 19, 20. <hi>Isaiah</hi> 30.10, 11, 12. <hi>Jer.</hi> 22.17. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 7.19. These and many other Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures came not in by way of a Concordance, nor yet as sought out by me, but they found me out, so that I once feared to open the book any more.</p>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:118224:5"/>
                  <p> But there <hi>was a book within me,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Isai. 29.18.</note> which though I would shut, and be willingly deaf to what was written therein, yet I was made to hear with a witnesse, <hi>Isaiah</hi> 33.14. <hi>The sinners of</hi> Zion <hi>are afraid, fearfulnesse hath surprized the hypocrites, who among us shall dwell with the devouring fire? who among us shall dwell with the everlasting burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings? he that walketh righteously, and speaketh uprightly, and despiseth the gain of Oppression, &amp;c. he shall dwell on high, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This was my morning thought,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>April,</hi> 8.</note> which made me rise up quick from my bed, and after second thoughts I hastened away to Church, where the Sheriffe and Judges were expected to come unto sermon, there I resolved in the face of all the Country to cast off the gain of Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pression, and burthen of Tithes, intending (with their Honours leave) in the end of all, to have spoken a few words on <hi>Psal.</hi> 68.5. But the Judges not coming that day to Church, the Preacher did no more but expound in the pue (there being but a thin Audience) upon this my former resolutions fell, and I thought within my self, surely the Lord would not I should openly meddle with this point, nor be too scrupulous in an outward thing, as this of Tithes, so I quietly heard the Man, and God also, in the very words then read, <hi>Eccles.</hi> 7.7. <hi>Surely Oppression maketh a wise man mad, and a gift destroyeth the heart.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For all this I returned home without the least touch, or trouble of conscience, saying, now I shall have peace and be still, provided for as formerly, I have been to <hi>offer up my Isaack,</hi> my beloved Tithes, but the Lord hath spared it and accepted me; I see <hi>a Ram caught in the bush for a Sacrifice,</hi> that is, my carnall mind and ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination, for now I looked upon this of Tithes but as a fleshly outward thing, a poor low business for any spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall man to be scrupulous of, therefore I said, I would go to my <hi>heights</hi> again, if once I might <hi>see the King in his beauty, and the land that is very farre off,</hi> Isaiah 33.16.17.</p>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:118224:6"/>
                  <p> The next day I came to your chamber, where I was welcomed with respect and kindnesse, but before I could sleep that night I was awaked again, and the Lord be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to <hi>answer in the secret place of Thunder,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Psal 81.7.</note> he that <hi>despiseth not the gain of Oppression shall not dwell on high.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Then down I came to the deep, and dwelt that night in the dark, in the shadow of death, yea, in the belly of hell, I cryed the next day also, <hi>O Lord I am oppressed, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake for me, Isai.</hi> 38.14.</p>
                  <p>This Scripture was that dayes Text; when I was to speak good things to the oppressed, I heard nothing but bad newes and sad tidings to my self, standing there under the <hi>gain of Oppression,</hi> I could experimentally tell this truth, that God would plague the oppressor, in whose stead (me thought) I was that day <hi>chattering like a Crane, and mourning as a Dove,</hi> in my cry, <hi>O Lord I am oppressed, undertake for me,</hi> it was answered, thou art an <hi>oppressor of men,</hi> and now thou art justly oppressed by God.</p>
                  <p>That was the summe of that morning exercise, how men oppresse God in mans oppression, and then that God oppresseth also their spirits as they doe his.</p>
                  <p>Truly to that time I never found the experience of this so true, <hi>The love of money is the root of all evill,</hi> evill of sin and of punishment, for by this I began, not onely <hi>to erre from the faith,</hi> and from trusting on God, but <hi>to be pierced through with many sorrowes, yea, to be drowned in perdition and destruction,</hi> 1 Tim. 6.9, 10.</p>
                  <p>And yet how often did my desire to be rich make me fear to be poor, and my proud heart seek to silence the cries of God and men within me, to shift off the thoughts of oppression, and the businesse of Tithes, as a thing not belonging to me, but for the States to reform? Again, my heart told me, that Tithes are now new modled and set in another form, with some moderation also.</p>
                  <p>And again, Tithes are coming into the Treasury of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:118224:6"/>the Common-wealth, God forbid said one within me, but thought I, why may not I take at present this free gift from the civill powers, as the Pastors, Teachers, and Preachers of the Gospel in <hi>Wales</hi> this day, who are maintained by Tithes.</p>
                  <p>Oh this renewed my former troubles, enraged those terrors, telling me, if now I be silent, I should not onely betray my Country, and the Governours of our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth to the judgement of God, but be base, and lye to the Churches, not speaking the truth, which many poor Christians, not attending to, doe daily wound their weak consciences by a little too much worldli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse (as in other things) so in farming of Tithes, which all the godly Preachers and people of God in <hi>Wales,</hi> did formerly profess, preach, and pray against.</p>
                  <p>Thus many Ministers also are unsensibly fallen into a new light, which themselves condemned in others, for my part I follow the old, and professe, that I can see yet nothing in Tithes but the <hi>gain of Oppression,</hi> continued and kept up meerly by Ministers, and Church-Members, who being men of power this day, might easily prevaile to remove this and many other oppressions, at least, with the people of the Land to petition the present Governours, to ease the oppressed of their burthens, as to release the prisoners from their bonds, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leive poor families with bread by a publick stock.</p>
                  <p>I speak not now of those Tithes which are part of mens temporal estates, but of such Ecclesiastick revenues appointed at first for Popish Priests, now for Preachers of the Gospel, this being a greater oppression than the tithes of former times, my spirit was oppressed by the Lord, till I had quite thrown away this abhomination, and burthen of the Land.</p>
                  <p>Thus then to me it is presented as more oppressive than Priestly Tithes; secondly, more oppressive than Popish Tithes; and thirdly, than Prelatick, or Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terian Tithes heretofore.</p>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:118224:7"/>
                  <p> First I say, Priestly Tithes under the Law had the command of God. Secondly, 'twas not forced on men by the power of the sword, but either freely given by the people, or urged by the Prophets with promises and threats to such who were disobedient or unwilling: Thirdly,
<note place="margin">Deut. 14.28, 29.</note> the Priests did not eat up all the Tithes them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, but as there was a yearly Tithe for the Priest, so every third year, there was a tithe for the poor; Oh, that the poor might have their Arrears out of the unreasonable gain of Gospel-Priests. Fourthly, Priests under the Law had but the tenth, our Preachers of the Gospel take up the fifth or fourth of mens lands and labours. Fiftly, the Priests who had Tithes paid them, had no other portion or temporal estate as most of our Ministers have, who may therefore preach the Gospel freely, if they can.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, they are more oppressive than <hi>Popish Tithes</hi> in forrain parts, <hi>France,</hi> the Kingdome of Asses (as 'tis called) hath not such an oppression in Tithes for their Priests, as our Protestant Teachers and Preachers of the Gospel doe burthen this free Nation; for as 'tis cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dibly reported by some, who have long liv'd in <hi>France,</hi> that there and in <hi>Spain</hi> also, onely Tithe of hard corn is paid, that is, of Wheat and Rye, but no Tithe of Barley, Oates, Pease, Beans, Fitches, Tills, much lesse Tithe of Hops, Hemp, Flaxe, Saffron, or of garden Hearbs.</p>
                  <p>Secondly 'tis not the tenth sheaf as ours, but onely the twentieth sheaf of Wheat and Rie is paid with them. Thirdly, if there be but nineteen Lambs, there is none, if thirty nine there is but one Lamb for the Priest, as one of twentie, and two of fortie is his Tithe, but our Gospel-Priests must have one Lamb of ten, yea, one of seven if there be no more. Fourthly ours have not onely the tenth Lamb, but tithe of the Wool of the nine remaining, wherers the Popish Priest hath no tithe of wool at all. Fifthly, They take no Tithe of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:118224:7"/>calves, hay, hay-grasse, or justments, much less tithe of pigs, geese, apples, eggs, and of every thing almost the poor live on, our Gospel Ministers must have their tithes.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly since the Independent Pastors are turnd Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons and Preachers of the Gospel, Parish Priests, the burthen of Tithes hath been more oppressive in them, than in the Prelates and Presbyters heretofore. For first, These were Nationall Ministers, and did service to every Parish in the Nation, therefore the National maintenance was more of right proper for them, but the Independent Churches, separating from the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and professing a Gospel-practice, cannot for shame deny their own Principles, as to keep up Tithes, but rather to look for a maintenance from their own Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, or to live of the Gospel, if they preach to the World, I say of the Gospel, that is, to live by faith in God, who will doubtlesse feed his servants, and cause men freely to contribute unto them who preach the Gospel freely. Secondly, The Tithes formerly were never so farmed out to Commissioners friends, who rackt the poor Parishioners to raise their own private gain, though they get forty or fiftie shillings yearly by the bargain. Thirdly, as 'tis more reasonable for the Parish to farm their own Tithes with the former a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batements, so in these times of publike Taxes, Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butions, and necessary burthens on the Nation, the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pression of Tithes is more intollerable, but our Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent friends load the people, who hoped to have been eased of all by their meanes. Fourthly, Godly men in <hi>Wales,</hi> who have suffred much for the State, and in tenderness of conscience could not pay Tithes to the Prelates of old, yea, who were indulged in those dayes, are now forced not onely to that, but to pay all their Arrears of Tithes formerly spared. Fifthly, as Tithes under this oppressive Form was first established by the Churches of <hi>Wales,</hi> who have given example for the English to follow the pattern and oppression; so con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:118224:8"/>what the Churches there have gained by this, even more Officers in the Church than ever Christ comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, as Commissioners, Treasurers, Sequestrators and Collectors for Tithes, a thing which neither Law nor Gospel, nor former Ages ever heard of. Sixt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<note place="margin">Hos. 6.8, 9.</note> God compareth such unto <hi>Thieves and Robbers: Gilead is a Citie of them that work iniquitie, and polluted with bloud,</hi> or as the Margen reads, <hi>cunning for bloud: And as Troops of Robbers wait for a man, so the companie of Priests murther in the way by consent;</hi> the <hi>Geneva</hi> notes <hi>Gilead</hi> to be the Citie where the Priests dwelt, and the <hi>companie of them</hi> was like a Synod or Classis. Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendents and Presbyters agree together and consent in <hi>Tithes.</hi> Seventhly, Doe not the Churches by this rob God also, (this at least being a Typical expression of their spiritual robberie) <hi>Will a man rob God? yet yee have robbed me,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Mal. 2.10, 14, 17. Mal. 3.7, 8, 13.</note>
                     <hi>saith the Lord: But ye said, Wherein have we robbed thee? In tithes and offerings,</hi> Mal. 3.8. Pray observe in this and in the former Chapters how oft God seeks to convince the Priests six times together, but the Priests will by no meanes be convinced by God himself of their manifest hypocrisie. Secondly, That God speaks to the Priests in both Chapters is plain from <hi>Mal.</hi> 2.1. <hi>And now, O ye Priests, this word is for you,</hi> and 'tis their word also, <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.14. <hi>What profit is it that we have kept thy Ordinances, and walked mournfully,</hi> Or as the Hebrew reads it, <hi>walked in black,</hi> that is their garbe, as <hi>Baals Priests</hi> are called <hi>Chemarim,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Zeph. 1.4.</note> or Black coats: Now, <hi>What profit is it</hi> (say they) <hi>that we have kept thine Ordinance?</hi> It is not Ordinances, but thine Ordinance, the Lords Ordinance (as I shall shew another time) is the Spirits presence and power from on high, this was the first Gospel-Ordinance, the Baptism of the Spirit and of Fire, for the appearance of the Spirit was on every Ordinance of the Gospel,
<note place="margin">Acts 1.4, 5. Acts 2.38. Acts 8.6, 28.</note> in water-Baptism, there was the promise of the gift of the Spirit, and the power of the Spirit in some visible gifts appeared with every one
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:118224:8"/>that did baptize in breaking of bread,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 12.13. 1 Cor. 14, 15. 2 Pet. 1.12.</note> they dranke into one Spirit, they did sing in the Spirit, pray in the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, preach the Gospel with the holy Spirit sent down from heaven; yea, in truth, all outward Ordinances of the Gospel were but the Ordinances of man, though appointed by God, the appearance and power of the Spirit was the Ordinance of God, but <hi>what profit</hi> (say the Priests) <hi>is it that we have kept thine Ordinances,</hi> waited on the Spirit, there's no profit in this.</p>
                  <p>Truly, the Spirits presence was more waited on, and the Saints in <hi>Wales</hi> were far more spiritual before their Church-fellowship, more simple-hearted, sincere, self-denying, and dying to the world, yea, though they walkt in Ordinances, there was no talk then of Ordinances, they were dead unto them (it being the worlds Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion) the Saints were all drawn up to the Spirit, which made them to be scoft of the world, which now they follow in their principles, practice, and desire of profit? <hi>What profit say they?</hi> Oh, there is no profit in the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits presence in the Ordinance of God; the power of men, the Ordinance for Tithes, and maintenance for Ministers hath more profit with it.</p>
                  <p>Well Friends, you must shortly walk in black, and mournfully with your Forefathers, the Prelates and Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters, because you follow their steps in the height of your Spirits, and lowness of your walkings, in your worldly designs, in your desires for profit, your tithes, augmentations, consolidations, Church offerings and such things, unheard of in Gospel-times, yea, it was a strange language to latter dayes.</p>
                  <p>But how doe the Priests <hi>rob God in tithes and offerings?</hi> the people rather should be said to rob the Priests in this, and yet it is proved before that all was spoken of the Priests, <hi>they rob God in Tithes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Certainly there's a Mystery in this (as in all other legall expressions (<hi>Mal.</hi> 1.11. <hi>Isai.</hi> 66.23.) For as Gods <hi>Tith or tenth</hi> is that small remnant of his people
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:118224:9"/>reserved from the Churches Apostasie, <hi>Isai.</hi> 6.13. <hi>In it shall be the tenth,</hi> &amp;c. So the <hi>Lords offerings</hi> is all the <hi>people of the land: Bring yee all the Tithes into my storehouse that there may be meat in mine house, Mal.</hi> 3.10. The Lords House is of a larger building then the gathered Churches have set up, as you may see <hi>Isaiah</hi> 66.19, 20. Where many Nations, yea, strange and savage people are brought into the house of God, who (I beleive) in his due time will gather these three Nations into one Church, (as the first fruits of his glory and fame to the world)</p>
                  <p>So then the <hi>whole Nation</hi> is the <hi>Lords offering,</hi> a Nation to be offred unto God. God is now rob'd of this offering by our Gospel-Priests, not onely the Tithes, the scattered Saints, but the Nation, even the Lords offering God is robbed of by the gathered Churches and their Priests.</p>
                  <p>For so it is clearer exprest by <hi>Malachy,</hi> c. 3. v. 9. <hi>Ye are cursed with a curse, for yee have robbed me, even this whole Nation,</hi> not that the whole Nation did rob God, as the words seem to import, but taking away the word [even] not in the Hebrew, the sence is clear, <hi>ye have robbed me this whole Nation;</hi> that is, as <hi>[God with us]</hi> is the Nations Motto, so God in the Nation, or the whole Nation, as the offering or people of God, the Independent Churches will not own, though the Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters in this are of a better judgement, who professe the Nation to be in Covenant with God, and his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and upon this account baptize all their children, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But sure 'tis a truth not onely in the Mysterie, but in the Historie or Letter, The Priests in Tithes and Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings doe <hi>rob the whole Nation,</hi> for the Nation is even ruined by the oppression thereof, Therefore our Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spel-Priests, who by the power of the sword take up their Tithes, or other wayes force a maintenance from the people, are called thieves and robbers by God.</p>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:118224:9"/>
                  <p> Oh how secretly and suddenly is the day of the Lord, or the Lords day stollen upon the Churches of <hi>Wales,</hi> Christ being come as a Theif in the night to spoil them of all their glory and honour, yea, their goodness is quite gone, and carried away into captivity.</p>
                  <p>For how hath <hi>God prophaned the Princes of the Sanctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary,</hi> or <hi>the holy Princes,</hi> as the Hebrew reads.
<note place="margin">Isai. 43.28.</note> The <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Princes</hi> in Church and Commonwealth are not onely become <hi>prophane,</hi> covetous, cruel, cunning for bloud, but they are prophaned by God, this the <hi>holy Princes</hi> will not hear that God should prophane any man, but now they may learn by experience, and be made to cry at last; <hi>Lord, why hast thou made us to erre from thy wayes, and hardned our hearts from thy fear,?</hi> Isai. 63.17.</p>
                  <p>Oh what prophanesse is this, that the holy Princes should be not onely proud, peevish, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but thieves and robbers in the way, to rob the whole Nation,
<note place="margin">Isai. 43.28.</note> to rob God and man at once?</p>
                  <p>No wonder, <hi>God doth give Jacob to the curse, and Israel to reproaches:</hi> This is worse then hanging it self to have the curse of God, and the contempt of man; truly it is far from my temper to reproach any man, much lesse the people of God, but if God shall give them to the reproach and the curse, what man can help it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I will send a curse upon you, and curse your blessings, yea, I have cursed them already, because ye have not laid it to heart,</hi> Mal. 2.2. <hi>Behold I will corrupt your seed,</hi> (or as the Margent reads, <hi>I will reprove your seed,</hi> and not onely the Word you preach, but the tithe-corn you gather for pay, and the tithe of your cattle too, <hi>I will spread their dung on your faces, and the dung of your solemn feasts, and thanksgiving dayes,</hi> when ye look up to bless my Name, <hi>I will spread dung on your faces,</hi> v. 3.</p>
                  <p>And then it followes <hi>one shall take you away with it, v.</hi> 3. One, Who is that? Sure there needs not the strength of many, but <hi>one</hi> man, yea, a babe in Christ can take away the Church with the Priest from their set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:118224:10"/>places. How easie is it for <hi>one,</hi> for a very child, with his little finger to push down all the Churches in <hi>Wales,</hi> being fallen already by their own divisions and defile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in worship, and in their walkings also, their wrath, worldliness, and which is worse, the thing of Tithes, wherewith they have foul'd their fingers.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Yee are departed out of the way, yee have caused many to stumble at the Law, (or in the Law) yee have corrupted the covenant of</hi> Levi, <hi>v.</hi> 8. Whats the Covenant of <hi>Levi?</hi> Oh to live in the Lord alone, to look for maintenance from him onely, no other maintenance but himself, for he was <hi>Levies</hi> portion.</p>
                  <p>Thus it was with <hi>Levi,</hi> and the Priests of old under the Law, the other Tribes had portions in the land, but the Lord God alone was <hi>Levies</hi> portion, and yet his al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance was from all, so <hi>Levi</hi> wanted nothing, though he had no portion but the Lord. Thus 'twas with the Apostles and Primitive preachers of the Gospel,
<note place="margin">Luke 22.35.</note> they went forth <hi>without scrip or silver in their purses,</hi> yet they <hi>wanted nothing,</hi> and having <hi>nothing, they possessed all things,</hi> 2 Cor. 6.10.</p>
                  <p>But our Gospel-Priests must have portions in the Land,
<note place="margin">Mal. 2.9.</note> or pay in their hand, else they will not preach: Therefore saith God, <hi>I have made you contemptible and base before all the people.</hi> Truly Sir, as I was forcibly carried forth to speak at first, so now to write my last, which I pray receive as the words of a dying man, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siring to dye to all things below God to my own life and livelihood.</p>
                  <p>Others preach for a hundred pound a year, I have now preached to lose it, in which indeed I have found my life, and a better livelihood in the Lord, who hath promised that he will not <hi>leave me, nor forsake me,</hi> Hebr. 13. And truly you may beleeve me, have more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, quietnesse, comfort in my present losse, and low estate,
<note place="margin">Mich. 5.7.</note> then in all my gainfull Tithes.</p>
                  <p>I then laboured to be rich, I now learn to bee poor,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:118224:10"/>to be Independent indeed, to <hi>depend on no man,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Micah 5.7.</note>
                     <hi>not to wait on men, nor the sounes of men,</hi> but on the mercifull providence and dispose of God for my abode and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Thus saith the Lord God,
<note place="margin">Jer. 49.11.</note>
                     <hi>Leave thy fatherlesse children, and I will preserve them alive, and let thy widdows trust in me,</hi> my children are now fatherlesse, and my wife a widdow, but God will be a father to them and a husband to her, yea, her Physitian also according to promise, <hi>Isai.</hi> 58.6, 7, 8. But all men are my flesh also, and because I would not <hi>hide my self</hi> from them,
<note place="margin">Isal. 58.7.</note> I had it once in my thoughts to take this hundred pound at present, and to give it as a publike stock for the poor of <hi>Cardiffe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It was presently answered unto me,
<note place="margin">Isai. 61.8.</note>
                     <hi>I hate robbery for burnt offerings,</hi> &amp;c. God will shortly provide for the poor, though Man will not: Yea, men shall at last, whether they will or no, when God shall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in them as fire to burn up all their fulnesse, when <hi>the rust of their silver shall eat up their flesh as fire,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iames 5.3. Isai. 2.20.</note> when they shall <hi>cast their Idols of silver and gold to the Moles and the Barts,</hi> who lye now in the dust, and flie in the dark. Lastly, In the day of wrath,
<note place="margin">Ezek. 7.19.</note> when they shall cast their silver in the Streets, then God will find a way to feed the <hi>poor out of the bellies of the rich,</hi> who shall not onely make restitution accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their substance, but shall vomit up all that they have swallowed, yea, it is a wonder, <hi>their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren shall seek to please the poor,</hi> and restore all their goods, <hi>Job</hi> 20.10, 15, 18. compared; I am waiting for the fulfilling of his Word, which God will hasten this in his due time, in mean while, I can but pitie the poor, and the rich also, even the great Oppressor, whose plague is coming, I have no more to say, but to assure you that I am in truth:</p>
                  <closer>
                     <salute>Sir,</salute>
                     <signed>Your much ingaged Friend<lb/> and Servant in the Lord,<lb/>
                        <hi>WILLIAM ERBERIE</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:118224:11"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:118224:11"/>
                  <p>A SCOURGE FOR THE ASSYRIAN, THE Great Oppressor.</p>
                  <p>According to the slaughter of <hi>Midian,</hi> by the annointing, <hi>Isai.</hi> 10.26, 27.</p>
                  <p>THAT IS, God manifest in Flesh, dividing and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroying that oppressive power in all Church Formes, and in the Spirits of the Mighty.</p>
                  <p>By WILLIAM ERBERIE.</p>
                  <q>
                     <p>Behold their valiant ones shall cry without, the Ambassadors of peace shall weep bitterly,</p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Isai. 33 7.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>G. D.</hi> for <hi>Giles Calvert,</hi> and are to be sold at the Sign of the Black Spread-Eagle at the West End of <hi>Pauls,</hi> 1652.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="letter">
                  <pb facs="tcp:118224:12"/>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:118224:12"/>
                  <head>To the Independent Pastors and Teachers in <hi>Wales,</hi> and in <hi>England</hi> also.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE great design that <hi>God hath to doe</hi> this day is to <hi>undoe man,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Zeph. 3.19 Hag. 2.22.</note> and the migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ones of the earth <hi>by dividing and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroying</hi> that oppressive power upon the <hi>states and spirits of men,</hi> that the <hi>outward and inward man</hi> may have deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance at last, and perfect liberty to <hi>serve the Lord in holiness and righteousness before him without fear all the dayes of our life.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Luke 1.75.</note> This was the end of <hi>Christs first coming in the flesh,</hi> and of his second <hi>in the Spirit,</hi> by which as <hi>the man of sin,</hi> the <hi>great whore Babylon</hi> must be destroyed: so divided <hi>into three parts,</hi> as in the slaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Midian,</hi> by the <hi>annointing</hi> by the Spirit of the Lord, or God manifest in our flesh, by whom all <hi>yokes</hi> and burthens are removed, <hi>Isai.</hi> 10.26, 27.</p>
                  <p>Now <hi>Babylon</hi> or the <hi>Assyrian</hi> being the <hi>great Oppres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sor</hi> in <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Common wealth,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rev. 17.3.</note> in the <hi>Civill</hi> and <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesiastick estate</hi> (for the <hi>Beast</hi> carries the <hi>Whore</hi>) both must be broken, as all the Prophets, and <hi>John</hi> the last doth prophesie: <hi>Babylon is fallen, is fallen,</hi> and a third fall wee shall see anon. <hi>How hath the Oppressor fallen,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Isaiah 14.4.</note>
                     <hi>the golden citie, the Lord hath broken the staffe of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and the rod of the Rulers:</hi> The rod of Oppressi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on appears not to men, but in the civil estate, and the staffe of the wicked there, but we shall <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                        <desc></desc>
                     </gap> the rulers or ruling Elders of Churches, we <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                        <desc></desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:118224:13"/>the wicked onely in the world,
<note place="margin">Ezek. 7.10, 11</note> but since the rod is bud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, pride hath blossomed, and <hi>wickednesse is grown up to a rod;</hi> the wicked may be found in the Church, in <hi>Israel</hi> it self: The Church I call now the people of God, in Church fellowship or not; but as <hi>among my people, saith God,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ier. 5.26.</note>
                     <hi>are found wicked men, who surpasse the deeds</hi> of the wicked: so since God hath <hi>prophaned the Princes of the Sanctuary,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Isai. 43.26.</note>
                     <hi>or the holy Princes,</hi> as I said before; there are principall men among the people of God, for whom the Prophet must cry and howle, because <hi>the Sword is drawn forth both against the righteous and the wicked,</hi> Ezek. 21.3. And <hi>against all the Princes of Israel,</hi> verse 12. Yea, the Sword is doubled the third time, the <hi>Sword of the great men, which enters into their privy Chambers,</hi> (or closest Councels) <hi>and the point of the Sword is set against their gates,</hi> (or Governments) that <hi>their hearts may faint, and their ruines be multiplied, ah it is made bright, and wrapt for slaughter,</hi> verse 14, 15.</p>
                  <p>But among <hi>all the holy Princes</hi> there is one especially whom the Lord calls upon, <hi>Thou prophane wicked Prince, whose day is come, when iniquity shall have an end,</hi> verse 25. <hi>Remove the Diadem, take off the Crown, this shall not be the same, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As King and Lords had an end, and twice the Sword hath been against the <hi>Prelatick</hi> and <hi>Presbyterian</hi> party, so the Sword being doubled, <hi>the third time will smite that prophane and wicked Prince,</hi> whatever he be, who is the Oppressor, who is <hi>imperious, proud, peevish, covetous, cruell and cunning</hi> for bloud; oh the Sword of the Lord will find him out, for 'tis <hi>wrape for slaughter,</hi> 'tis wrapt, I say, and <hi>secretly 'twill come forth,</hi> to cut off the man that stands before God, to oppose <hi>the appearance of God in men,</hi> to oppresse the spirits of men, and the Spirit of God in them, <hi>the Sword of his mouth shall slay him,</hi> 2 <hi>Thess.</hi> 2.8.</p>
                  <p>I shall not now meddle with matters of State, nor of secular men (though these also may come under the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:118224:13"/>King of <hi>Babylon</hi>) but our Lords spirituall are those here who are called <hi>the King of</hi> Babylon, <hi>against whom thou shalt take up a Proverb or a taunt, saying, How hath the Oppressor ceased? The golden City</hi> ceased, <hi>Isai.</hi> 14.4.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The golden City</hi> is the most glorious Church state, or the people of God in highest honour and glory; this <hi>is the golden City,</hi> or (as the <hi>Geneva</hi> reads) the <hi>Gold thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting City, the exactresse of Gold,</hi> as the margin notes.</p>
                  <p>None doe more exact, and more thirst after Silver and Gold this day, then <hi>the people of God in spirituall power,</hi> and therefore no wonder they doe so oppresse both the states of men, and the spirits of men, yea, the Spirit of God, as may be seen at large, <hi>Micah</hi> 2.2, 6, 7. compared with 8, 9, 10. verses, <hi>Even of late my people is risen up as an Enemy, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Oh the great Oppressor! how the earth doth rejoyce at the ruine of that man, <hi>who smote the peogle in wrath</hi> with a <hi>continuall stroke, that ruled the Nations in anger,</hi> (no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of love, mercy, and goodnesse to mankind, or the poor, appeared in him) <hi>but he persecuteth and no man hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth,</hi> saith the Prophet, <hi>Isaiah</hi> 14.6, 7, 8.</p>
                  <p>And as the <hi>whole Earth is merry at his fall,</hi> so <hi>hell from beneath is moved for him, to meet him at his coming it stirs up the dead, and even all the cheif ones of the earth, and all the Kings of the Nations rise up from their Thrones, they say, art thou also weak as we? art thou become like unto us?</hi> verse 4.10.</p>
                  <p>What are the <hi>people of God,</hi> and <hi>Princes of Israel the holy Princes, so prophane?</hi> Is the <hi>prophane Prince of Israel so weak?</hi> weak as the imperious whorish woman? <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.30. Art thou so weak as we? weak in thy passions and pettish Spirit? art thou become like unto us, as one of the Kings of <hi>England,</hi> or the Princes of <hi>Wales?</hi> What man would think, that the Church or People of God should ever come to this, to oppresse both God and man, good and bad at once? But this is naturall to spirituall men in Church formes, yea, to the flesh of the best
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:118224:14"/>Christians,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 3.3. Gal. 4.29.</note> who may for a time be very fleshly, and yet the children of God, as <hi>Ishmael was Abrahams sonne after the flesh, persecuting him that was born after the Spirit;</hi> yea, Saints by calling may be called carnall, much more <hi>when they are become so wise after the flesh, so mighty, and so noble,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Cor. 1.26.</note> which must have an Almighty power of the Spirit, to make them foolish, and weak, and base, and nothing, to bring to nought things that are; the great things and Conquests here attained by the people of God was when they were nothing, now being something they are overcome by all, and by themselves.</p>
                  <p>When men doe adore the people of God, and idolize them as <hi>the Gods of the earth,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Zeph. 2.11.</note> then a thousand to one, <hi>God does befoole and famish them,</hi> and they fail to be proud, and to oppress the world, yea, their own Brethren, and their Father also, even the most high God, appearing in lowest Saints above them in grace, and the knowledge of our Lord, in simplicity, in purenesse, and peace, and in patience also.</p>
                  <p>Well this is the thing that God will <hi>doe with his own,</hi> he will <hi>undoe them,</hi> either by the high discoveries of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self in them, as the Prophet was, <hi>Isaiah</hi> 6.1. who came to this, that he saw himself, though as good as the best, yet as bad as the worst, <hi>verse</hi> 3, 5. Or else he will undoe them, by discovering that without to the world which is within in the heart,
<note place="margin">1 King. 8.38. Iam. 3.6.</note> what <hi>a plague is</hi> in it? <hi>what a sinke and sea of sin?</hi> yea, a hell is in the tongue, this the Saints will not see, but God does, and men shall, when he shall turn their inside out, their hidden hypocrisie shall appear to all, for they shall openly <hi>practise hypocrisie,</hi> as men doe grosse prophaneness, for <hi>the vile person shall be no more called liberall, nor the Churle said to be bountifull, &amp;c.</hi> Isaiah 32.5, 6, 7. see it.</p>
                  <p>Alas man, <hi>Thou maist give all that thou hast to the poor yet have no love:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Cor. 13.3. Tit. 3.4. 1 Ioh. 4.16.</note> Oh belye not the Spirit of God in thee, for <hi>God is love, and good to all mankind,</hi> while thou art a <hi>murtherer</hi> in hating <hi>thy brother, John</hi> 3.15. yea, in not
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:118224:14"/>loving him so as to <hi>lay down thy life for him,</hi> verse 16. much more in not laying out thy livelihood, and <hi>this worlds good,</hi> verse 17. not onely for the godly, as they say, but for any man that needs thee, who is both thy brother and <hi>thine own flesh,</hi> Isaiah 58.7.</p>
                  <p>Nay tis not enough that thou art no Oppressor, as I said before, but <hi>to loose the bands of wickednesse,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Isai. 58.6.</note>
                     <hi>to undoe the heavy burthens, to let the Oppressed goe free, and to break every yoak is the duty of love, if there be power in thine hands to doe it.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But when the people of God are silent, and sit still, seeking onely self, not sensible of the <hi>burthens of the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed,</hi> of the <hi>Prisoners bands,</hi> nor of <hi>poor families who cry for bread,</hi> how dwelleth the love of God in them, saith <hi>John.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Well, want of love, besides worldlinesse, wrath, and that oppressive power in the Churches,
<note place="margin">Gen. 49.7. Isai. 19.2. Ier. 51.49.</note> is the cause why they are so divided among themselves, yea, <hi>God divides them</hi> (as he did <hi>prophane them</hi>) <hi>he sets Brother against Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Ruler against Ruler, one ruling Elder against another.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>'Tis Rule and Government the Churches still aime at, therefore they not onely dash one against another, but are like to destroy that civill Government, and the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours they depend upon, for since the Apostacy, the Churches have ever had a dependance on worldly powers, and undone the powers with themselves, and therefore our present Governours are wise to beware of men.</p>
                  <p>But Men, and Ministers, and Churches, as we see, are divided this day like <hi>Babylon</hi> into three parts, as we shall shew anon, and so their destruction is of themselves; I say, they seek for rule, and this ruines them.</p>
                  <p>Now there is a threefold kind of Government among men <hi>Monarchy, Aristocracy,</hi> and <hi>Democracy;</hi> the first is as of the King, the second is like that of the Parliament, the present Government some compare to the third, though it appears not yet, but Parliament and Army have voted
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:118224:15"/>the Supream power to be in the people.</p>
                  <p>Well, the Churches must have power and rule also, the Prelatick Church was <hi>Monarchicall,</hi> all were ruled by one, by an Arch-Bishop, the Kingly Power or Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative fell by that: The Presbyterian Church is an <hi>Aristocracy,</hi> the Elders or chief of these govern as 'twere in a Parliament, and Parliamentary priviledges was like to fall by them, if not fallen already: The Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent, or baptized Churches (both is one) are a pure <hi>Democracy,</hi> for not the ruling men, or Ministers, but all the Members, have equall power to order and ordain as they professe, and therefore called Independent, I wish they were so, but if they have a dependance on the Civill or Martiall power, 'twill be worse for both, if both be not wiser than former times.</p>
                  <p>A word to the wise, 'tis my folly to use so many to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding men as the Ministers are, especiall Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, being men of parts, power, policy, and of piety al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so many; I shall fear none of them, because I love them all, and they me, though wrath at present may appear in both, as it doth among themselves ('twas so once be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween God and his own people of old, a perfect hatred, <hi>loathing and abhorring one another.</hi>)</p>
                  <p>Well, the Vials are yet full of the wrath of God, when these are poured forth, Love will appear, that is, the Lord himself in us all, who will bring forth light out of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, and love out of our divisions: And as he <hi>in wrath remembers mercy,</hi> so in much love, I pray you, remember</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your, <hi>WILLIAM ERBERIE.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="treatise">
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:118224:15"/>
                  <head>A Scourge for the Assyrian, the great OPPRESSOR:</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>ZACH. 11.8.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>Three Shepherds I cut off in one moneth, my soul loathed them, and their soul abhorred me: <hi>That is, the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Appearance of the great God in men, is most abhorred by seeming godly men, and Ministers, or</hi> three Shepherds, <hi>whom God therefore loathes, and hates all</hi> their performances, as they hate his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance, <hi>the hatred of both is perfect,</hi> for his soul loathes them, and their soul abhorreth him.</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S Christ is the <hi>glory of the Father,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Heb. 1.1.3. Iohn 14.10. Ioh. 15.23, 24 Isai. 8.18. Hebr. 2.12, 13 compared.</note> the appearance of God, or <hi>God manifest in flesh;</hi> so <hi>God</hi> in <hi>Christ,</hi> the <hi>Father in him,</hi> was that which was most hated by the <hi>Church of the Jews,</hi> and <hi>Christ in us;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iohn 14.11 Eph. 5.30. Heb. 2.11. compared.</note> Christ in the Church is abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the <hi>Christian Churches;</hi> who not knowing the <hi>Deity</hi> nor the <hi>humanity</hi> of Christ in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, will not acknowledge the <hi>Father</hi> to be the <hi>God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head of Christ,</hi> nor his <hi>brethren to be his humanitie,</hi> in whom the fulnesse of the Godhead is so embodyed,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 12.12. Eph. 4.13. compared.</note> that he being the <hi>head,</hi> and they the <hi>members,</hi> they and he make <hi>one perfect man,</hi> in whom God appears to be <hi>all in all,</hi> 1 Cor. 15.28.</p>
                  <p>This <hi>Mysterie of God, even the Father,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Col 2.2.</note>
                     <hi>and of Christ</hi> is
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:118224:16"/>therefore abhorred by the <hi>shepherds,</hi> or Pastors of Churches,
<note place="margin">Gal. 1.16. Eph. 1.17. Col. 1.27. compared.</note> because they knew not the <hi>Father</hi> in the Son, nor the <hi>Son</hi> in the Saints, nor the <hi>Spirit</hi> in both, which would reveal <hi>this glory in them,</hi> God in their Flesh, that is <hi>Christ in us the hope of glory,</hi> which now they <hi>hate and abhor,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Col. 2.8.</note> not having higher discoveries of God, then what they have read in traditional forms of <hi>do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine received,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Tim. 1.17. 1 Ioh. 1.1. Rom. 9 1. Heb. 1.3.8. Col. 1.15.19. Col. 2.9. compared.</note>
                     <hi>and invented by men.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For as the Father is <hi>the invisible God</hi> inhabiting eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, so Christ is <hi>God visible,</hi> the Image or out-goings of God, the glory of the Father (in flesh) the appearance of God, (as I said) or <hi>God manifest in flesh,</hi> who in the spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit was from the beginning, and willbe to the end, though this <hi>mystery of Christ</hi> was not manifested to men till the <hi>fulness of time,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Isai. 9, 6. Ioh. 5.19, 20, 30. Iohn 8.28. Iohn 14.10 compared. 2 Cor. 13.4. 1 Pet. 1.21. Psal. 68.1. Psal. 68.18. Eph. 4.10. Ioh. 16.28. Iohn 17.8.</note> when the <hi>mighty God, the everlasting Father</hi> appeared in flesh, taken of a Virgin, then the <hi>Son was born,</hi> for God was brought forth in flesh, and was manifest in flesh <hi>by mighty works and words which he spake and did,</hi> while he lived in the dayes of his flesh, but in his death, <hi>God crucified that flesh to himself,</hi> which af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward <hi>he raised to glory, God rising</hi> or revealing himself gloriously therein, then God <hi>ascended up on high,</hi> that is, <hi>God in flesh</hi> did ascend not onely to <hi>heaven,</hi> but far <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all heavens,</hi> into his own <hi>eternall abisse, and incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehensible being, and unaccessible light,</hi> whence the <hi>bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of his glory proceeded,</hi> and came <hi>forth in flesh</hi> in the fulness of time, as we said before.</p>
                  <p>But this Mysterie was not <hi>made known nor manfested</hi> to the <hi>Sons</hi> of <hi>men,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Eph. 3.5.</note> till God who <hi>ascended up in flesh,</hi> sent down the <hi>Spirit from on high,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Psal. 68.18. Eph. 4.8.</note> when he not onely <hi>recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved gifts for men,</hi> or as Hebrew reads, <hi>received gifts in the man, but gave gifts unto men;</hi> that is, the same Spirit and power of God, dwelling in the flesh of Christ, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared in the Church which is called Christ, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.12. because the <hi>Son</hi> was <hi>revealed,</hi> or known in the Saints, and they in the <hi>Son,</hi> and <hi>both in the Father,</hi> all perfect in one; for which cause the Spirit is called the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:118224:16"/>
                     <hi>promise of the Father,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Acts 1.4. Rom. 8.25.17.</note> and the <hi>Spirit of the Son</hi> in the Saints <hi>cryed, Abba Father,</hi> God being a Father to them as to him, his God and theirs. For though the Spirit be called the Spirit of the Son, yet he received and sent it from the Father, therefore the Spirit is said to <hi>proceed</hi> onely from the <hi>Father,</hi> &amp;c. it is the <hi>promise of the Father,</hi> the power of God from on high, which the Saints received from and with the Son, they being Sons and coheirs with him, <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.26. This Mystery of Christ though once <hi>manifested to the Apostles and Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Saints by the Spirit,</hi> and since shut up as a <hi>sealed book</hi> by the apostasie or spirit of Antichrist in the Churches, yet the <hi>book will be open, the mystery will be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifest again, for the mystery of God shall be finished,</hi> and fully known at last, <hi>Rev.</hi> 10.7.
<note place="margin">Rev. 1.4. Rev. 2.8.</note> But as Christ is <hi>the first</hi> and <hi>the last,</hi> he who <hi>was, is, and is to come,</hi> so Christ <hi>was</hi> vayled in the Law, and <hi>is</hi> revealed in the Gospel, (though but in part) the full Revelation of Christ Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus is <hi>to come,</hi> Jesus Christ the <hi>same yesterday, and to day, and for ever,</hi> not Christ after the flesh, for that was not till <hi>the fulness of time,</hi> but Christ in the Spirit, <hi>God manifest in flesh,</hi> was both <hi>yesterday</hi> under the Law,
<note place="margin">Heb. 13.8.</note> and in the <hi>day</hi> of Gospel-dispensation, and in the third dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pensation now approaching, he will abide <hi>for ever.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>There was a change indeed from Law to Gospel, when the Spirit of Christ first came into the Church; the state of the Gospel changed also, when the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Antichrist</hi> came in power, and the Churches fell by the Apostasie; when Christ shall come the second time <hi>in spirit and glory, time shall be no more,</hi> no<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc></desc>
                     </gap> more change of things shall be, for <hi>all things and times shall appear in eternity,</hi> which is the third dispensation, as the first was <hi>yesterday,</hi> the second to <hi>day,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rev. 10 6,</note> so the third is to be <hi>for ever.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I shall not now speak at la<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc></desc>
                     </gap>ge of this third <hi>dispensati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> onely as <hi>God is both Fa<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                           <desc></desc>
                        </gap>n, and Spirit;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Joh. 5.7.</note> So God being manfest to his <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                        <desc></desc>
                     </gap> threefold discovery
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:118224:17"/>of himself, declares the <hi>third dispensation,</hi> a third disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verie of himself unto them, and in them.</p>
                  <p>God <hi>under the Law</hi> and to the Fathers before was known as <hi>the Father.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Deut. 32.6.</note> In <hi>the Gospel</hi> God was known, as <hi>the son,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rom. 1.9.</note> or the knowledge of the Son was peculiar to the Gospel-dispensation.
<note place="margin">Rev. 22.17.</note> The third will be <hi>pure Spirit,</hi> when nothing but Spirit and power shall appear, when God shall be all in all: For although Gospel-believers were baptized into the name of Father, Son and Spirit, yet what they possessed was but <hi>the first fruits of the Spirit,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rom. 8.23.</note> there will be a full harvest, flouds, and <hi>Rivers of waters of life which no man can passe over,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ezek. 47.5. Isai. 11.9. Hab. 1.14. Zach. 14.8. Rev. 22.1. compared.</note> when the <hi>earth shall be full of the knowledge of the Lord</hi> (or as another Prophet adds) <hi>full of the knowledge of the glory of the Lord, as the waters cover the Sea,</hi> Isai. 11.9. <hi>Hab.</hi> 2.14. There the Lord God Almighty and the Lamb, God even the Father, and Christ the Fathers glory shall be fully known by men;
<note place="margin">Rev. 21.22. Rev. 22.4.</note> For as <hi>Christ is the appearance of God,</hi> so when <hi>God shall appear in men</hi> they shall know how Christ <hi>was</hi> under the Law, and as he <hi>is</hi> in the Gospel, and will be the same <hi>for ever.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>All that I know at present of Christ is this, he was under the Law in <hi>Forms:</hi> In the Gospel hee appeared in <hi>Flesh,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Tit. 2.13. Heb. 9.28.</note> he will appear wholly <hi>in Spirit,</hi> in Spirit one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the <hi>appearance of the great GOD and Saviour shall be,</hi> and yet <hi>manifest in the flesh of men,</hi> that is, all the transactions of God, or all that God did in the flesh of Christ,
<note place="margin">Rev. 12.5. Rev. 11.8, 11, 12. 1 Cor. 6.2, 3. Obad. 21. compared.</note> shall visibly appear in the flesh of men; the birth of Christ, his life, death, resurrection, and ascention shall be seen in us, men shall see us <hi>ascend in a cloud,</hi> to sit in heaven to <hi>judge the world and Angels,</hi> and to bee <hi>Saviours of men in mount Zion at last.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For the <hi>Lamb shall bee in mount Zion, and with him we shall be,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rev. 14.1.</note>
                     <hi>having his Fathers name on our foreheads,</hi> that's the full discovery of God in us, and men shall see God, even the Father in us with Christ, so cleerly manifest as <hi>written on our foreheads.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:118224:17"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Mount Sion</hi> is not an outward Church-state, as the Churches now imagine, and call themselves, though they be indeed the <hi>daughter of Babylon;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Zach. 2.7.</note> but <hi>Zion is</hi> the <hi>state of all the Saints in the Spirit as they are in God, and God in them:</hi> For as <hi>Zion</hi> was the place where God dwelt; so all the Saints from the beginning of the world have been still waiting for this, for the full discoverie of God in them. <hi>Glorious things were spoken of Zion,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Psal. 87.3.</note> and the people of God both under the law, and in Gospel-dispensation were still going on <hi>from strength to strength,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Psal. 84.7.</note>
                     <hi>till every one of them appears in Zion before God</hi> Every one appears at last in Zion, <hi>Rev,</hi> 14.1. not onely the <hi>hundred and fourscore and four thousand,</hi> who go before, and are the first fruits unto God, <hi>v.</hi> 4. but a number<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less company of men, (<hi>whose voyce was as many waters, and as a mighty thunder,</hi> vers. 2. For as the hundred fourscore and four thousand is the just number of the sealed ones. <hi>Rev.</hi> 7.4. selected out of the twelve Tribes, who were first called the <hi>Church and people of God,</hi> typi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying those in the last dayes who shall be <hi>redeemed from men, and the first fruits unto God,</hi> as we said before; so afterward there will be a company of people called to God whom no man can number, <hi>Rev.</hi> 7.9. But these come to <hi>Zion through great tribulation, through the bloud of the Lamb in them,</hi> v. 14. that is, through much suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, through the <hi>fellowship of Christs suffering, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity to his death</hi> they come to rise, and raign with him, having <hi>palms in their hauds;</hi> that life of Gospel-Saints which was <hi>hid with Christ in God,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Col. 3.3.</note> shall appear in God, and the life of God shall appear in the Saints at last, thus Christ <hi>their life shall appear in them with glory.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This glorious appearing of the great God, rising up in higher discoveries of himself in men, is that which hath been ever most opposed and persecuted; I speak not now of the times under the Law, nor Gospel, nor yet of former appearances, since the Apostasie. But
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:118224:18"/>to goe no further then our own age, what we have heard and seen: How was the appearance of God in the First Reformers, yea, in our Prelates and Bishops per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secuted as heresie by the Popish Hierarchie! Next the honest Presbyters or Puritans how were they opposed by the same Prelates, who suffered before? Thirdly, these Presbyterians formerly themselves in a suffering condition, persecuted the appearance of God in those of higher forms and fellowships, as the Independent Churches; and these likewise are ready to oppose and persecute the spirits of the Saints, who in worship and doctrine are of higher discoveries then themselves.</p>
                  <p>The doctrine of <hi>God and of Christ</hi> for substance is the same in all the Saints, though their apprehensions dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, or are divers rather. And who is ignorant of this, that the appearances of God in one man, hath not been the same as it was formerly in himself? and yet all have been going on from <hi>strength to strength,</hi> at least in their desires and aimes toward Zion.</p>
                  <p>Though I am but a child in underdanding, and in yeares also to some of our Elders, yet here I observed four great steps of Gods glorious appearance in mens preaching.</p>
                  <p>First, how low and legall were their teachings, as they learnt the way of preaching from Mr. <hi>Perkins, Bolton, Byfield, Dod,</hi> and <hi>Dike,</hi> most blessed in their ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, by whom, and such conforming Ministers, more men were converted to God, then ever since in any period of time.</p>
                  <p>Next the Doctrine of free Grace came forth, but with lesse successe or fruit of conversion, by Dr. <hi>Preston, Sibs, Crispe,</hi> yet many before converted were confirmed and comforted by their words.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, the letter of Scripture, and the flesh of Christ hath been highly set up by both the famous <hi>Goodwins,</hi> the one, Master <hi>John Goodwin</hi> like <hi>Apollos</hi> being migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in Scriptures and strength of reason; the other ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:118224:18"/>in spirituall discourses of Christs death, resur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, ascension, and intercession, yet much accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the flesh; for he meddles not with the Mystery of Christ in us, of his dying in us (as Mr. <hi>Dell</hi> in part discovers) but all of Christ without us, which though a truth, yet not the whole truth, nor that spirit and truth which Christ spake of;
<note place="margin">John 6.63. 2 Cor. 3.6.18</note> for <hi>as the flesh profiteth nothing, but the quickning spirit that dwelt therein;</hi> so the the Apostles had a <hi>ministery of the spirit</hi> to carry men through the flesh of Christ into the Father, that eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Spirit dwelling in him and them, and so to draw them up into the same fellowship with himself.</p>
                  <p>Again this good man speakes much of Christ in the flesh, not as <hi>he is in the Father, and we in him, and he in us,</hi> which is the sum of our spiritual knowledge, and all we should know of Christ after his Ascension, <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.20.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, he brings us no further then to the <hi>vail of his flesh,</hi> not <hi>through it into the holy of holiest,</hi> into the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head it self, that is, into the Father, for Christ was but our fore-runner, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 6.19, 20.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, though the vail of <hi>his flesh</hi> be <hi>a new and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving way into the holiest,</hi> yet not that flesh as <hi>living,</hi> but as dead and <hi>crucified, became the living way, Heb.</hi> 10.20. (as with God) I shall shew another time.</p>
                  <p>Fifthly, that worthy man brings men to the <hi>way,</hi> but not to the <hi>Truth and Life:</hi> Now Christ was all, First, the <hi>way for no man cometh to the Father, but by me,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iohn 14.6.</note> now 'tis a vain thing to keep men still in the way, to stand still in the way, and not to goe on by Christ into the Father, <hi>into the holiest,</hi> and thus was Christ <hi>the Truth,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iohn 14.3.</note> also <hi>taking us into the Father with himself,</hi> for as this was <hi>eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life to know the Father to be the onely true God,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ioh. 17.3.</note>
                     <hi>and Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ whom he hath sent:</hi> so Christ was sent, or God even the Father was manifest in his flesh, that <hi>we might see God in us, as he was in him,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iohn 17.21, 23, 24.</note>
                     <hi>and our life with him in God:</hi> Lastly, thus <hi>Christ is the life,</hi> and thus he that
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:118224:19"/>hath the Son hath life, that is, the Son being once re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed in us, reveals the Father in us also, God in our flesh as in his, and we living with him in God alone, <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.19, 20. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.11, 12.</p>
                  <p>This is the knowledge of Christ in the Spirit, and this is the fourth step which some have attained to, holding forth Christ in the Spirit, as Mr. <hi>Sedgwick,</hi> Mr. <hi>Sterrie,</hi> Mr. <hi>Sprig</hi> and others, these with their fellows are nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest Zion, yet are they not come into it; for as every Prophet shall one day <hi>be ashamed of his vision;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Zach. 13.4.</note> yea, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phesie it self shall fail: So it is manifest these men are of a <hi>dark and deeper speech then can be easily understood,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Isai. 33.19.</note> therefore it is not Zion, when there shall be such a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious appearance of God in men, that all shall see and hear him in them, and as they <hi>shall see eye to eye, when the Lord shall bring again</hi> Zion,
<note place="margin">Isai. 52.8.</note> (or bring forth himself cleerly in us, who are now in captivity, or he rather captive in our flesh) so men shall hear God himself in us, for so it is in the Hebrew, <hi>Zach.</hi> 8.23. not <hi>we have heard that God is with you,</hi> but (we will go with you for) <hi>we have heard God with you, and in you.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Then man shall be nothing, and God shall be all in all, yet man shall be all in God, and nothing but God shall appear in man. This glorious appearance of the great God in man, the <hi>three Shepherds,</hi> the Pastors and Teachers doe <hi>indeed abhor,</hi> they <hi>hate his appearance,</hi> (as I said) and he <hi>abhors</hi> all their performances.</p>
                  <p>But who are these three Shepherds? the Pastors of Churches: What their cutting off is my former Letter shewed, to suffer the curse of God, and contempt of men: How God cuts them off? it is by unchurching them, and by confounding or dividing them, the Lord doth first unchurch them, burns up the Church with fire, <hi>Zachariah</hi> 11.1. there he calls <hi>Lebanon to open the doors,</hi> that the <hi>fire may come in to burn up the tallest Cedars.</hi> Whats Lebanon but the Temple, for it was built with that: Who are the Cedars? but the tallest
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:118224:19"/>Members, the <hi>principall of the flock:</hi> What is the <hi>fire?</hi> but the Spirit of the Lord: as the Lord God calls upon <hi>Lebanon,</hi> so he commands that the <hi>Church doors</hi> may be open <hi>for the fire to enter,</hi> and the spirit to burn up all their chiefest members and Ministers, for so it is <hi>vers.</hi> 2. <hi>The mighty men, or the gallants are spoiled,</hi> yea, there is a <hi>howling of the shepherds for their glory is spoiled,</hi> v. 3. Their Church-fellowship and forms is that they glory in; God spoils them, <hi>and stains the pride of all their glory,</hi> yea, he burns it up; How? By fire; <hi>The baptisme of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and of fire</hi> was the first Gospel-Ordinance,
<note place="margin">Acts 1.4, 5.</note> or that which first set up the <hi>Church in a Gospel-order.</hi> Fire will be the last that shall burn up the Churches, who because they would not, as the Primitive Saints did, wait for the Spirit to build them, the Spirit shall come to burn and consume them at last.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, God cuts them off, confounds and divides them, he cuts them into three parts as we shall see by and by.</p>
                  <p>Thus then the <hi>three shepherds</hi> are the Pastors of all the Churches or whole Ministery of the Church; for as the Apostate Jewish Church was a Type of the Christian Church now under the Apostacie (the <hi>whoredomes of Isreal,</hi> typifying the <hi>great whore,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ezek. 16.30. Rev. 17.2.</note> whose fornications and the wine thereof in their forms of doctrine and false worships) as we shall shew another time: so <hi>Junius</hi> well notes the three Shepherds to signifie the whole teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Ministery of the Jewish Church,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Vid. Junium</hi> in Zach. 11.</note> for the Pharisees Sadduces, and Essenes (saith he) were the onely Pastors or Teachers, who did instruct the people in the Word of God, as Prelates, Presbyters, and Independents are the whole Ministery of the Church of <hi>England</hi> this day.</p>
                  <p>These are divided not onely in Worship, and Disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, but in doctrine also, especially in three things 1. In the free grace of God, which some call Antinomianism 2. In the free-will of man, which otherscall Pelagianism. 3. In the death of Christ, or universal Redemption
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:118224:20"/>of mankind thereby, which both Presbyters and Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendants abhorre as Paganisme, though nearest the <hi>Gospel indeed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I shall not now shew the cause of all those divisions in Doctrine, being engaged onely at present to prove their defilements in the worship of God, and in their walking with men.</p>
                  <p>Yet this is one cause of their former difference and divisions in Doctrine,
<note place="margin">Acts 2.42.</note> because <hi>the Apostles Doctrine,</hi> being before all Gospel-Ordinances, is out of order in the Churches,
<note place="margin">1. Tim. 6.3. 2. Tim. 1.13.</note> who not content with that <hi>forme of sound words,</hi> and <hi>wholsome Doctrine delivered</hi> by them, doe follow the childish Dictates of Fathers, the Decrees of Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels, being a company of Bishops, with such Creeds, Confessions, and Catechismes, formed by them (and reformed Churches) whose conformities and fooleries in formes of worship, though our Churches cannot chuse but see, yet with a blind devotion they follow all their formes of doctrine, not suffering a doubt or the least debate to passe upon their reason and judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment therein.</p>
                  <p>How injudicious this is with ingenuous men let all men judge,
<note place="margin">Iohn 3.12.</note> for if I <hi>tell you of earthly things,</hi> saith Christ, <hi>and yee beleeve not, how will yee beleeve if I tell you of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly?</hi> all outward worship is but an <hi>earthly thing:</hi> Now if all Fathers and former Churches have erred in worship, why not, I pray you, may they not erre in Doctrine, in heavenly and hidden things in the high Mystery of God and of Christ? especially seeing the Apostles did prophesie of <hi>such deceit to come in this, by vain</hi> Philosophy,
<note place="margin">Col. 2.8.</note> and metaphysicall speculations of the Deity, <hi>by the traditions and inventions of men, the rudiments of the world,</hi> the rudiments, that is, the A. B. C. or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Catechismes, which is the Religion of the world, and of little Children.</p>
                  <p>Another cause of divisions in Doctrine is this, the confidence of men and Ministers, who conceive, that
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:118224:20"/>Christians know God and Christ already, whereas themselves are ignorant of both,
<note place="margin">Rev. 1.7. os Rev. 5.2.</note> not minding that <hi>God is a Mystery,</hi> and that the Mystery of <hi>Christ hath been a sealed Book</hi> ever since the Apostasie, as I have shewn, in a book of <hi>neither Truth nor Error,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Nor Truth, nor Error, &amp;c. page 6.</note>
                     <hi>nor Light nor Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, but in the evening there shall be Light.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thirdly, Their darknesse and divisions hath been caused by not <hi>knowing Christ in the Spirit, nor understand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Mystery of Christ,</hi> for all Christian Religions have been doting onely on the flesh of Christ: See the Papists how they look upon Christ in a Picture; so Protestants have their <hi>pleasant Pictures also,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Isai. 2.16, Ezek 16.17.</note>
                     <hi>the Image of a Male,</hi> as the Prophets phrase it, that is, fleshly <hi>ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehensions of Christ,</hi> which they adore and deifie: thus the <hi>Arminians</hi> and <hi>Socinians</hi> goe no farther than Christ after the flesh, and the last especially, though religious and most learned men, yet look no higher than flesh; yea, the eternall Spirit and infinite God they confine to a place in Heaven, where, say they, his essentiall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence is, though his power be every where, a very carnall conceit of God and of Christ.</p>
                  <p>But what mystery can the <hi>Socinian</hi> see in the Man Christ, if the Man be not God, or <hi>God manifest in flesh?</hi> is not the Man Christ <hi>the Mystery of God? Rev.</hi> 10.7.
<note place="margin">Col. 2.2. Eph. 3.5.</note> And how can <hi>the Mystery of God and of Christ be mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest but by the Spirit?</hi> 'tis neither strength of reason, nor reading of Scripture, but the Spirit onely, even the <hi>Spirit of Revelation,</hi> that can prove the Godhead of Christ, therefore the Apostle himself had it, <hi>not as he received it of man, nor as he was taught it, but by the Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Josus Christ,</hi> when it pleased God to reveal his Son in him, &amp;c. <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.12, 15.</p>
                  <p>For how could the Apostle, preaching to the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, prove the Godhead of Christ by Scripture to them, who owned neither Christ nor Scriptures? But <hi>Christ speaking in him,</hi> that is, Christ in the Spirit,
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 13.3.</note> God powerfully acting and appearing in <hi>Pauls</hi> flesh, did so
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:118224:21"/>manifest the Mystery to them, that by <hi>the power of God working in him mightily,</hi> he was able to present every man in Christ, that is, <hi>in God,</hi> and God in them, and <hi>they his Off-spring,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Col. 1.28, 29.</note> and thus did he prove the Godhead of Christ, and that God would judge <hi>the world by the man Christ Jesus,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Acts 17.28, 29, 32.</note> even by the manifestation of God in <hi>the Saints, who should judge the world with them</hi> and in him, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.2.</p>
                  <p>Indeed to the Jewes, who acknowledged the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, by Scriptures he proved that Christ was God, yet not the Godhead of Christ by that, for as Christ never said that he was God (but <hi>sent by God</hi>) so he shewed his Godhead to <hi>be the Father dwelling in him, and doing all his works,</hi> which though neither the Jewes nor Disciples clearly saw in the dayes of his flesh; yet when he should <hi>depart to the Father,</hi> and the Spirit or <hi>Promise of the Father</hi> should be sent, then the power of God appearing in their flesh as in his, he <hi>shewes them the Father plainly,</hi> for as <hi>no man knowes the Father but the Sonne, and he to whom the Sonne reveales him;</hi> so I said before, that God, even the Father, must reveal the Sonne in us, by the Spirit of Revelation to us, else there is no knowing the Godhead of Christ at all, <hi>John</hi> 14.10. <hi>John</hi> 16.25, 27, 28.</p>
                  <p>For <hi>no man can say that Jesus is the Lord,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Cor. 12.3.</note>
                     <hi>but by the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit;</hi> alas man, what mystery is it that Christ is God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause God made the Man so? because God gave him that name? gave him that power and glory as God? 'tis true, that Christ, even the Sonne of God, had all by gift of the Father,
<note place="margin">Iohn 5.19, 22, 26. verses.</note>
                     <hi>The Sonne could doe nothing of himself, God gave him even the Spirit, gave him authority to judge, gave him to have life in himself</hi> (whereas we have all of him,
<note place="margin">Math. 28.18. Iohn 17.2. Phil. 2.6, 9. Heb. 1.8, 9.</note> and by him) <hi>God gave him glory, all power in heaven and earth; God gave him a name above every name,</hi> yea, <hi>gave him to be called God, for God, his God, annointed him to it</hi> above his fellowes; all this proves not the Godhead
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:118224:21"/>of Christ, but that he was the <hi>Man Gods fellow, that is, equall with God, in the form if God,</hi> as 'tis parallell'd by the Apostle and Prophet, <hi>Zach.</hi> 13.7. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.6, 9.</p>
                  <p>Therefore what <hi>Socinus</hi> saith, that Christ is God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause God gave him that name, that power, that glory, and honour, is no mystery, for God can give <hi>to a Worme, to thresh the mountaines, tothrow down the earth, to destroy and judge the world,</hi> Isai 41.14, 15. Jer. 51.20.</p>
                  <p>But what's the Mystery of Christ? <hi>wait for the Spirit to manifest it</hi> to thee and me: <hi>Till the seventh Angell sound,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rev. 10.7.</note>
                     <hi>the Mystery of God shall not be finished nor fully known.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>What a madnesse is it then, for men to warr and wrangle about that they know not? Is it not better for us, to wait in peace and patience, forbearing one another, and embracing one another in love, till the Lord God appear in all?</p>
                  <p>I shall therefore crave pardon of all men, because I cannot chuse but say, that <hi>no man yet knowes God, nor Christ, nor himself;</hi> this makes the difference and divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion (as I said before) because men are so confident, and therefore contend of the free Grace of God, the free Will of Man, and the Death of Christ, yet they know not <hi>God as he is,</hi> nor what <hi>Man is in God,</hi> nor what <hi>the Man-God Christ is,</hi> in the Mystery, how in God, and how he is in man: Oh yee <hi>Protestants, Papists, Arminians,</hi> and <hi>Socinians,</hi> answer me this one question; Why did the highest Apostle beg the prayers of all the Churches, that he might know the <hi>Mystery of Christ,</hi> that he might manifest it, and that he might <hi>speak as he ought to speak?</hi> Eph. 6.19, 20. Col. 4.3, 4.</p>
                  <p>You think you know Christ, and can preach him well enough, we shall be all silent, and God himself shall speak at last, and speak himself, and manifest himself unto men: Oh that men could watch and wait in love together to that day!</p>
                  <p>This is the last thing I had to observe, that all the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:118224:22"/>
                     <hi>speaking and preachings of men will be silenced by God</hi> when the Lord appeares: Pray but observe in those four steps before mentioned, of Gods appearance in men, how the power, efficacie, and fruit of Conversion hath decreased: The Doctrine of Free-grace converted fewer than that legall teaching before; the preaching of Christ after the flesh by the purest Churches hath had lesse converts yet; yea, those who preach Christ in the Spirit, the most seraphick Sermons, call in but few Sinners, though some Saints may be raised, others proud flesh rankle thereby; but as for the Spirit of Jesus, where does it appear in mens preaching or pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctise, or the power of godlinesse?</p>
                  <p>That which I conclude from this is, that <hi>God is going out, and departing from all the preachings of men,</hi> that men may give themselves wholly to publick acts of love one to another, and to all mankind; therefore all <hi>religious formes</hi> shall fall, that the <hi>power of righteousnesse</hi> may rise and appear in all:
<note place="margin">2 Pet. 3.13. Rev. 21.22.</note>
                     <hi>The new Heaven and new Earth, where dwelleth Righteousnesse, hath no form</hi> of Religion there.</p>
                  <p>I see 'tis hastening by many things, and this to me is the least prophetick providence and experience in the present powers of the Nation: when the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> first began, oh what speakings were there? what Speeches of severall Members of the house of Commons were printed every week? but now the Common-wealth comes on, there is more of Action done every day, and though the Parliament many times say more than they doe, yet they doe more than they say, which is best of all.</p>
                  <p>Again, I cannot but observe, that as <hi>the falling of a Sparrow,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Math. 10 30.</note>
                     <hi>or the smallest hair of our heads, is subject to the speciall</hi> providence of God; so 'tis remarkable that all the Parliaments Ordinances are now turned into Acts, for Acts indeed are better than Ordinances, these are of form, those of power; the Army was best in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed when they were about their Ordinances, their
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:118224:22"/>Guns, going forth for common freedome, those were their Acts, and God did blesse them therein in all their publick actings, and in their publick Spirits, but as for their publick speakings, their Declarations, Protestati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Remonstrances, 'tis not worth a rush: So are their Councels of War, when judging the Consciences of men in the Mystery of Christ (a most high presumption:) yea, all their fasting and prayer before God is not worth a pins head, till they repent and return to their first principles, to the power of Righteousnesse, to Justice, and Mercy to the Nation, without all self-seeking, striving for the universall good of mankind, even for Papists and for Jewes themselves, to live with freedome and comfort among us, <hi>Mal.</hi> 1.9, 10, 11. compared with <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.4, 5.</p>
                  <p>This is the <hi>glorious appearance of the great God,</hi> not to talke and prate of things, but to be working and acting, to be ever doing good, as <hi>Christ did alwayes to all,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Acts 10.38.</note> and though there was a Ministery of men once to speak also glad tydings and good things to men, yet since the Apostacy, that <hi>Apostolick Ministery being silenced,</hi> and the <hi>manifold gifts of the Spirit</hi> ceased, and no man sent of God to <hi>preach the Gospel which the holy Spirit sent down from Heaven,</hi> all is but earth and man that is said,
<note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.12.</note> the number of the <hi>beast being the number of a man,</hi> Rev. 13.16.</p>
                  <p>And though God hath hitherto <hi>fed and led the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man in the wildernesse,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rev. 12.6.</note>
                     <hi>and caused men to minister some truth and peace to his</hi> people under the Apostacy, yet this was but <hi>his Free-grace,</hi> and high <hi>Prerogative of love,</hi> who as not tyed to meanes, so by a false Ministery could convey light and comfort to his own; but now God is pouring vials of wrath on that which was once lovely, upon the Sun and air, upon the light of man, upon the meanes, and those mediums that receive it, Rev. 16.8.17.</p>
                  <p>Again, seeing the man of sinne, the mystery of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:118224:23"/>is now more revealed in the Temple of God than ever, and the ministery of men is discovered every day not to be of Gods appointment, as Prelates, and Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters, and purest Independent Pastors, cut off by the Lord himself: it is therefore judged, that not onely the whole Ministry, but all the preachings of men, will shortly be silenced by the glorious appearance of God.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Be silent O all flesh, for the Lord is raised out of his holy habitation, Zach.</hi> 2.13. Why if man be silent, what will God doe among men? <hi>A Father of the fatherlesse, and a Judge of the widow, is God in his holy habitation, Psal.</hi> 68.5. that is, God will so appear in men, that instead of speakings, they shall goe forth in actings of love to mankind, and to the miserable part thereof, to the <hi>poor, to the oppressed, to the fatherlesse, and the widow,</hi> and to all that want that which we abound in.</p>
                  <p>As this was once <hi>pure Religion, and undefiled before God even the Father,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iam. 1.27.</note>
                     <hi>to visit the Fatherlesse and widow in their afflictions, and to keep our selves unspotted of the world;</hi> so the neglect of this is charged on the Apostate Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, <hi>Isai.</hi> 1.23. <hi>Jer.</hi> 5.28.</p>
                  <p>Alas, what is it to send Preachers abroad before the burthens and oppressions of the people be eased?
<note place="margin">Exod. 6.9.</note>
                     <hi>Israel it self could not hear, because of the sore bondage in Aegypt;</hi> I say, not all burthens taken off, because the charge of the Common wealth encreaseth, but why may not rich Citizens, racking Landlords in the Country, and mighty moneyed men, be made immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately to rise in their payments, that poor Farmers, La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourers, and honest Tradesmen may be spared? Why not oppression be presently eased, at least of Lawyers and Tithes? Why not a Treasury for the poor, when so many thousands a year can be found out to give to the rich? would that hinder the publick more than this? It is the goodnesse of the State indeed, to honour and conferre gifts on high deserving men, but it is disho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:118224:23"/>and base for such to receive it, who neglecting the publick good, seek their private gain, who would seem to be Saints and self-denying men, yet forgetting their vowes to God and men, care not though the poor and the oppressed sink, starve, and dye, so they may live fat, and full, and free from those evils.</p>
                  <p>Gifts are as bad as bribes, when Justice and great things are to be done in a Nation, for as a bribe blindes the eyes, and they <hi>shall never see the King in his beauty,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Isay. 33.15. Eccl. 7.7.</note>
                     <hi>who shake not their hands from holding of bribes, and despise not the gain of Oppression;</hi> so <hi>a gift destroyes the heart,</hi> that the most publick spiritted man dares not think a good thought, much lesse to speak or act for common free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and the good of mankind, while money stops the mouth, choakes and <hi>destroyes the heart.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>They say indeed the time is not yet come, but <hi>is it a time to receive monie?</hi> said <hi>Elisha:</hi> Oh say others,
<note place="margin">2 King. 5.26. Isai. 51.14.</note> you are to hasty, &amp;c. but the <hi>captive exile hastened that he might be loosed, and that he should not dye in the pit, nor that his bread should fail:</hi> If these men were banished but for a year, or their Babes without bread for a day, they would not delay justice and mercy to men, seeing the Lord <hi>comes riding on a swift cloud,</hi> to judge and raign, and to <hi>hasten Righteousness,</hi> Isai. 16.5.</p>
                  <p>Let <hi>Mercurius Politicus</hi> tell you the reason of State, and shew you <hi>if men were religious inde<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc></desc>
                        </gap>d, that is, righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, just, honest, plain, simple hearted people, they might quickly doe</hi> what they say: what's that? <hi>Take away the iniquity of the Land in one day;</hi> the iniquity, that is,
<note place="margin">Zach 3 9.</note> the oppression, &amp;c. <hi>I will take it away in one day;</hi> how so I pray?</p>
                  <p>When God shall appear in men,
<note place="margin">See the Lord of hosts, or Armies de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, pag. 23.</note>
                     <hi>and men act in the immediate power of God,</hi> when the power that God and man hath put into their hands is improved to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most, <hi>without fear of man,</hi> and with full <hi>confidence in God,</hi> oh what a <hi>world of good might be done in one day?</hi> all the proud enemies, oppressors, the unrighteous riches, the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:118224:24"/>unjust gaines, the great reveneues suddenly got, yea all the <hi>iniquity of the Land would be taken away in one day.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This would be <hi>Gospel indeed, and glad tydings to the poor,</hi> and make all the oppressed in the Land to sing, for this is <hi>the everlasting Gospel</hi> which shall be preached, <hi>not in word but in power,</hi> not as the Gospel at first, in speaking, or <hi>preachings, but in publick actings, the everlasting Gospel</hi> shall goe forth in the last times, as I shall hint anon, and another time (with God) more fully prove, that the <hi>preaching of the everlasting Gospel</hi> is not the ministery of man, nor is that <hi>Angel</hi> a man or Minister, but the <hi>Angel of the Covenant, Christ in us,</hi> God in our flesh, that is, God fully manifest in us shall minister himself to us, God shall minister himself to men, a pure Ministery of the Spirit shall be, the Spirit shall onely minister both light and love among men, salvation, and strength, suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciency, and fulnesse of all good things to the whole Creation at last.</p>
                  <p>This <hi>glorious appearance of the great God and Saviour in men,</hi> is that which is most <hi>abhorred by Ministers and Pastors, three Shepheards,</hi> whom the Lord <hi>loaths and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vides</hi> because they will not be drawn up to union, and love to mankind, to whom they are rather cruell, <hi>their throat an open Sepulchre,</hi> and their feet <hi>swift to shed bloud;</hi> that is, they will speak no <hi>good will to man,</hi> but swallow down the most and destroy them, not owning <hi>all men as their own flesh,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Isai. 58.7.</note> and God the eternall Spirit dwelling in them, therefore God divides the Shepheards with their flockes, dashing one against another, causing <hi>every man of them to eat the flesh of his brother,</hi> Zach. 11.9.</p>
                  <p>True, it is but <hi>flesh and fleshly formes</hi> the Churches fight and contend for, the cause of all the contention is in the Shepheards or the Ministers, the Church-members, poor soules would be quiet, and come up again to walk in the Spirit; but because the Members will follow, not the Head, but their fellowes, Members and Ministers,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:118224:24"/>God <hi>gives them up to their King,</hi> v. 6. Who is that? Sure some chief Pastor who commands in Church and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth: Well, for this, God takes no more care of the Church, but divides them also; <hi>He breaks the Covenant which he made with all the people,</hi> v. 10.</p>
                  <p>The Independent Church was built once on a <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant,</hi> now being ashamed of that, they call it a <hi>confession,</hi> others an <hi>agreement,</hi> God breaks all in pieces even the Covenant. First his <hi>staffe,</hi> Beautie, that is, the <hi>unitie of the Spirit,</hi> v. 10. then his <hi>staffe bonds,</hi> the bond of Peace, for the <hi>brotherhood between Judah and Israel is broken, verse</hi> 14.</p>
                  <p>How cleer doth this appear in the present Churches, who by a Law call none brothers but such of their own societies, no Saint whatsoever, nor yet Christ were he among them would they call brother, unlesse he were of a Church way, and of theirs also, therefore the bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therhoood between <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Israel,</hi> (the Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and baptized Churches) is broken.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Great and marvellous are thy works Lord God almighty,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rev. 15.3.</note>
                     <hi>just and true are thy wayes thou King of Saints?</hi> How just is it for God to divide those Churches that divide them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves from Saints? How true is their division, when the very <hi>Brotherhood</hi> is broken?</p>
                  <p>Oh <hi>love the brotherhood,</hi> saith <hi>Peter,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.17.</note> that cannot be saith the Prophet, for there is nothing but wrath and wars to be among them, they must be divided and sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>divided also: <hi>I will deliver the men every one into the hand of his neighbour, or fellow member, and into the hand of his King or Pastor,</hi> for such are called Kings in Scripture,
<note place="margin">Zach. 11.6.</note> Princes of the Sanctuary. Again, saith God, <hi>I will not feed you, that that dyeth let it die, and that that is to be cut off, let it be cut off, and let the rest eat every one the flesh of another,</hi> v. 9. that is, those fellow-Members who were more moderate and peaceable minded men, not given to common division, are yet destroyed and die in their spirits, by being in Church-fellowship, for God
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:118224:25"/>breaks the <hi>Covenant that he made with all the people,</hi> v. 19.</p>
                  <p>This is that I shewed in the mountaines from <hi>Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiel</hi> 37.3. That, <hi>All the people of God this day are a dead divided people,</hi> not onely gathered Churches, but scatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Saints, these in their flesh, those in their forms and fellowships.</p>
                  <p>First, they are as dry <hi>bones of the valley,</hi> yea, bones ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>dry</hi> lying in the <hi>open valley,</hi> the lowest part of the earth, and it is the <hi>open valley,</hi> every one above them who are on the hills may behold and see how <hi>dead</hi> and <hi>dry</hi> they are; very dry saith he, having neither skin, nor sinew, nor strength, nor spirit, nor yet flesh indeed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, not the letter of Scripture for any of their publique Worships, common Prayers, &amp;c. nor yet in their walkings doth the flesh Christ appear upon them in meekness and lowliness of heart, yea they are not so lowly and loving, as once they were, so humble and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly minded, so self-denying and dying to the world. And as they are dead so divided into two sticks, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 37.16.
<note place="margin">See Zeph. 3 9. a pure lip and perfect love or union will not be on earth, till the earth or Church, in her divisions and defile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments be burnt up with fire, which is <hi>Babylons</hi> last plague, Rev. 18 8. then men will serve or worship God in Spirit, and with one con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent or shoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</note> they are not now called <hi>branches, but sticks,</hi> dry, sapless things without any shew of spiritual life, yea with out hope to rise here on earth, as themselves con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse, <hi>v.</hi> 11.</p>
                  <p>But I have better hopes of you beloved, then your selves have: All the Churches indeed shall fall, but the Saints therein shall rise, <hi>Oh my people</hi> saith God, <hi>I will open your graves, and cause you to come forth out of your graves,</hi> v. 12.</p>
                  <p>But there the people of God yet are, and this the Lord would haue them know this day, although they will not that they are all in <hi>Babylon, dead dry bones,</hi> and <hi>divided sticks:</hi> Dead in <hi>their formes,</hi> divided in <hi>their fellowships,</hi> and <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc></desc>
                     </gap>efiled in both, <hi>Zeph.</hi> 3.9. But <hi>Babylon</hi> is yet di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided into <hi>three parts,</hi> for since the Apostacie the Churches have been still divided <hi>into three parts,</hi> as the <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Latine</hi> Churches of old, and the <hi>Affrican</hi>
                     <pb n="45" facs="tcp:118224:25"/>Church that made the third, there was the <hi>Eastern, We<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stern,</hi> and <hi>Southern</hi> Churches: So in the <hi>North</hi> at the first Reformation, the <hi>Calvinist, Lutheran,</hi> and <hi>Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tists</hi> in <hi>Germany.</hi> Thus it is in <hi>England,</hi> the <hi>Prelatick, Presbiterian,</hi> and <hi>Independent</hi> Churches are <hi>Babylon</hi> divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into three parts.</p>
                  <p>The Apostolike Churches or Churches of Christ were but <hi>one bodie,</hi> had but <hi>one Baptism,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Eph. 4.4.</note> as there was but <hi>one Spirit</hi> leading all the Saints in one Church way, one <hi>way of worship,</hi> one <hi>Church government</hi> was among all the Saints, though there were differences between bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and brother, yea, between one Apostle and another, yet never was there a division <hi>between Church and Church</hi> as in <hi>Babylon</hi> this day, for the Spirit being then but one, kept the body in one Baptism. But now the Churches are become <hi>three bodies,</hi> and these have <hi>three Baptisms;</hi> Presbyterians <hi>baptise the whole Nation;</hi> Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendents the <hi>children of beleevers onely;</hi> the baptized Churches <hi>beleevers themselves:</hi> Here is <hi>Babylon</hi> in three parts: Again the baptized Churches are subdivided in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to three parts, one Church is for <hi>free will,</hi> a second for <hi>universal Redemption,</hi> a third count themselves more Orthodox in Doctrine, as the Church of <hi>England:</hi> Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of these three baptized Churches dare communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate one with another, Oh <hi>Babylon! Babylon</hi> is fallen is fallen, for <hi>Babylons</hi> fall is by division and confusion;
<note place="margin">Isai. 10.26, 27 Iudg. 7.25. Ioel 3.12.</note> the Prophet calls it, <hi>The slaughter of Midian,</hi> for the <hi>Midianites</hi> were destroyed by their mutual division. This another Prophet calls the <hi>valley of Jehoshaphat,</hi> for as the scattered <hi>bones lay in the valley,</hi> Ezek. 37.1. So the valley of <hi>Jehoshaphat</hi> hath some reference to the dry bones, and the divided sticks in <hi>Babylon.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Whats the valley of <hi>Jehosaphat?</hi> 'Tis the divided state of men opposing the appearance of God in his people. See 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 20.23. there is <hi>Moab, Ammon,</hi> and <hi>Mount Seir,</hi> all three of kin to the true Church of God, which those three came against, as the present
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:118224:26"/>Churches pretend to the Primitive Church of Christ, which yet they oppose in the Spirit.</p>
                  <p>Well, let us look into the <hi>valley of Jehosaphat,</hi> thither <hi>cause thy mighty ones to come down O Lord,</hi> saith <hi>Joel</hi> 3.11. Oh how many mighty ones, and high spirited men are come down <hi>to the valley of Jehosaphat, into divided Churches, Moab, Ammon,</hi> and <hi>mount Seir:</hi> First, two are against one, then one against another, for <hi>Moab,</hi> and <hi>Ammon,</hi> stood up against <hi>mount Seir utterly to slay and destroy, and when they had made an end of the inhabitants of mount Seir, each man helped to destroy one another,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 20.23.</p>
                  <p>Thus it was with the <hi>Prelatick, Presbyterian,</hi> and <hi>Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent</hi> Churches, these two last <hi>stood up, utterly to slay and destroy</hi> the first both Root and Branch, and now they <hi>help to destroy one another,</hi> as Independent and bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized Churches both against Presbytery, and now <hi>these two against each other:</hi> Yea, the baptized Churches them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves are divided into three parts, are now in destru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction by <hi>their own divisions:</hi> Sure it is by the <hi>annointing</hi> all this is done, the <hi>Spirit</hi> of the Lord in their flesh, which would unite doth now divide them, because they will not hear <hi>what the Spirit saith to the Churches.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Therefore it is said before 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 20.22. <hi>The Lord set ambushments against the children of</hi> Moab, Ammon, <hi>and mount Seir,</hi> &amp;c. an ambushment in <hi>secret and sudden assault of an enemie</hi> unawares: Oh how <hi>secretly and sud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly</hi> hath the Lord come upon the Churches in their <hi>march</hi> and <hi>Church-way?</hi> how hath he <hi>divided them one against another,</hi> before they were aware of it. This is the <hi>Lords work,</hi> and the <hi>wonder of men,</hi> that men who are all godly cannot joyn in <hi>one Church-way?</hi> why they will not, they shall not, they cannot, for God <hi>divides them in Jacob, and scatters them in Israel.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As this is <hi>Babylons</hi> judgement to fall by division, so it is the judgement of God on the Churches, for in the <hi>valley of Jehoshaphat he sits to judge.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:118224:26"/>
                  <p> That which I have heard to be Mr. <hi>Brightmans</hi> opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and Mr. <hi>Sterries</hi> since, was given into my Spirit long ago, that as the seven Churches of <hi>Asia,</hi> signifie the <hi>State of the Apostolike Churches</hi> inclining to an <hi>apostasie:</hi> So <hi>Laodicea</hi> the <hi>last tipifies the latter Churches</hi> this day, who indeed shall be the <hi>last in the world,</hi> and the fall of all shall be first in <hi>England,</hi> for as Mr. <hi>Brightman</hi> holds <hi>Laodicea</hi> to be the Church of <hi>England,</hi> so the Churches here are <hi>Laodicea</hi> indeed, lukewarm, without heat, or the Baptism of fire at all, the Lord condemnes the other Churches in some things, yet in something he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends them, but the Church of <hi>Laodicea</hi> he commends not at all, but condemns altogether, because she was <hi>well, and wanting nothing,</hi> no Church-order, no Ordinance is wanting to them.</p>
                  <p>Whats <hi>Laodicea</hi> in Greek,
<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc> in non-Latin alphabet </desc>
                        </gap>.</note> but the <hi>judgement of the people,</hi> the people of God are judged indeed in the <hi>val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley of Jehosaphat</hi> this day, by their mutuall divisions to their utter destruction.</p>
                  <p>Therefore thus saith the Lord, <hi>Three shepherds I cut off in one moneth.</hi> What's this <hi>moneth?</hi> Sure it is a Myste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. In general it is very shortly, as <hi>Junius</hi> before, for the Lord will now doe a <hi>short work on the earth,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rom. 9.28. Isai. 19.1.</note> he comes riding on a <hi>swift cloud</hi> to judge; yea, the Lord <hi>is a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness too, and a swift witnesse</hi> against the Churches,
<note place="margin">Mal. 3.5.</note> he comes <hi>quickly,</hi> and he will make <hi>but short work with them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I will not speak of the Popish Church which conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued so many hundreds of yeers, look but into our own land in these last dayes, wherein the mysterie of Iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty hath been most manifest, not onely by the Spirit, but by sensible experience, and the event of things in a very little time.
<note place="margin">The King could give them no more time. The Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment gave them just so much.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Prelacie upheld by <hi>Kingly Power</hi> continued about seventy years, inssaving the people of God, like <hi>Israels captivitie of old in Babylon.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Presbyterie reigned but three <hi>years and a half</hi> (the time of the <hi>Beast</hi>) by <hi>Parliamentarie Authoritie,</hi> for no
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:118224:27"/>longer according to Ordinance their time was to last.
<note place="margin">The Armie cannot give so much time as that, for <hi>time shall be no more</hi> Rev. 10.6. nor yet <hi>times, nor half a time,</hi> for thats the 42. <hi>moneths,</hi> the <hi>Dragons</hi> time. Revel. 13.5.42 <hi>moneths</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>three years</hi> and <hi>a half,</hi> that is <hi>time, times, and half a time, time</hi> is one year, <hi>times</hi> two years, and <hi>half a year</hi> is the half time which shall be no more saith <hi>John,</hi> 'tis now but a moneth, nor forty two, nor time at all.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Independency is down in a <hi>moneth,</hi> thats a shorter time then the former, they are fallen before they rise, the whole Armie cannot help them up again.</p>
                  <p>But what is this moneth? It is that of the <hi>wild Asse in the Wild rness,</hi> the Lord compares the Church to this, <hi>Jer,</hi> 2.24. <hi>A wild Asse used to the Wilderness, that snuffeth up the wind at her pleasure, in her occasion who can turn her away, all they that seek her will not weary themselves, in her moneth they shall find her.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>What is the <hi>moneth</hi> that we may find <hi>the Asse,</hi> for men weary themselves in vain to seek her, she is <hi>so wild,</hi> and in the <hi>wilderness</hi> also, where she <hi>holds up her head,</hi> and <hi>snuffs the wind</hi> as she goes, neither will <hi>she be turned out of her way,</hi> yet in <hi>her moneth she is found;</hi> Whats that! It is the <hi>moneth that she is ready to bear or bring forth,</hi> when she is full of pain and travell, when the <hi>wild Asse</hi> is in a <hi>suffering condition</hi> she may be found.</p>
                  <p>Thus it was with the Churches; The Prelates thought themselves Preachers of the Gospel, how high did they hold their heads, <hi>and snuffe the wind as they went,</hi> but when their suffering time came, the <hi>spirits of Princes</hi> were cut off, the proudest Prelate dared not open his mouth for his eares, that shewed him an Asse, for if he had been as he said a Preacher of the Gospel, all the Parliaments of the world should not have stopt his mouth, but they had no more to say when they came to suffer, then without seeking a man might find them to be no Ministers of the Gospel, <hi>for their moneth was</hi> come.</p>
                  <p>It was just so with the Presbyters, when in power with the Parliament, they-also were as <hi>wild as the Asse</hi> in the <hi>Wilderness,</hi> as proud as the Prelates, and held up their heads as high, and opened their mouths (against hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven) as Ministers of the Gospel also, but when <hi>the moneth</hi> of their sorrows and sufferings come to an end, they
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:118224:27"/>will be dumb <hi>as the Asse,</hi> and as Bishops were, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less God by a Miracle open their mouth, as <hi>Balaams</hi> Asse to speak freely, the next countermand that comes from the Powers can silence them, or if they suffer the losse of Tithes, all their mouthes are stopt at once, for <hi>their moneth</hi> is come, they are cut off by God, and can preach no more.</p>
                  <p>Well, the Independent Pastors and Teachers their moneth comes (and that in one day as <hi>Babylons</hi> plague did) I will not compare these wise men to the Asse in the Wilderness, yet truly they will not be turned from their way,
<note place="margin">Hos. 12.1.</note> but snuffe the wind as they goe (<hi>for it is wind that</hi> Ephraim <hi>feeds on</hi>) Oh, when will their moneth be? Whence can their sufferings arise, seeing the whole State, and the highest Souldierie is for them? For all this they must suffer, all the world cannot save them, but what shall their sufferings be? Surely <hi>not from man, nor by man, but by the Lord God they shall suffer,</hi> as it is cleer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly foretold, <hi>Isai.</hi> 31.8, 9. <hi>The Assyrian is the last Oppres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sor,</hi> for <hi>Egypt</hi> was before. The Churches this day doe <hi>oppresse not onely men in their States, Mic.</hi> 2.2, 8, 9. but the <hi>spirits of men,</hi> vers. 6. Yea, the <hi>Spirit of God</hi> also, vers. 7.</p>
                  <p>The present Churches I look upon as the <hi>Assyrian</hi> the last oppressor that shall be in the Land, this is the <hi>Assy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian that shall fall?</hi> How! not <hi>by man, and the sword not of a mean man shall devour him, Isai.</hi> 31.8. How shall the Assyrians fall be then? First, by fear. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, by fire. <hi>The sinners of Zion are afraid already, and begin to fly to their strong holds,</hi> and hope in an Armie or arm of flesh, <hi>v.</hi> 8. What makes them <hi>fear and fly?</hi> Oh there is an <hi>Ensign set up in the Saints,</hi> v. 9. the glorious ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of God in the <hi>scattered Saints</hi> makes the <hi>ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered Churches</hi> quake and fear; but where is the <hi>fire?</hi> Why it is in Zion, <hi>and his furnace in Jerusalem,</hi> v. 9. What is <hi>Zion but the Saints in whom God dwels,</hi> or in whom God discovers himself to be. Is he not in the Churches
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:118224:28"/>also? Yea, the Lord is there among them, the <hi>everlasting burnings is in them,</hi> yea, they shall finde and feel short<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that <hi>consuming fire</hi> to break forth upon them, and to <hi>burn up all their flesh and forms.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This is the judgement of God still on the Churches, because they would hasten to a Church-way, not waiting for the <hi>Baptism of the Spirit, and of fire</hi> to set them in a Gospel-order, or to shew <hi>them a higher glory to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed in them;</hi> therefore a fire shall come forth of their own bowels to burn them, that is the fire of his jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie: Thus they are gone from one fire into another, as <hi>Ezekiel</hi> tels them, <hi>They shall go out from one fire and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother fire shall devour them,</hi> Ezek. 15.7. they are gone out of the <hi>fire</hi> of the <hi>Spirit,</hi> the <hi>fire of his jealousie</hi> shall consume them, <hi>Zeph.</hi> 3.3. I speak not now of their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons but of that oppressive principle and fleshly power, thats the Assyrian in them, as I said once, that of old the people of God <hi>were in Babylon,</hi> but now <hi>Babylon</hi> is <hi>in them,</hi> especially in the Churches called the <hi>oppressor, the golden Citie,</hi> Isai. 14.4.</p>
                  <p>But see how the fire is come in to the Churches as we said before,
<note place="margin">Zach. 11.</note> there not onely the Cedars, the tallest and highest members are burnt, <hi>v.</hi> 2. but all the mighty men (or gallants) are spoiled, even the Ministers or Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stors, for the howling of the Shepherds is heard on high, <hi>v.</hi> 3. &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Pray observe in all the Prophets what plagues are foretold to fall upon the <hi>Pastors and Shepherds of Israel;</hi> but especially <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> Ch. 25.34, 35, 36. where there is a great <hi>howling of the Shepherds and principall of the flock, for the day of their dispersion is come,</hi> or their division as we said before, <hi>Zach.</hi> 11.6, 9. Here they doe <hi>eat every one the flesh of another,</hi> of his fellow or brother, as the Hebrew reads; thus the fellow-members fall out, and the <hi>bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therhood is broken</hi> between the Churches, <hi>v.</hi> 14. Why? because their Shepherds are <hi>cut off</hi> in one <hi>moneth;</hi> whats that? we have said already 'tis the <hi>day of their sufferings.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:118224:28"/>
                  <p> But there may be another sense of this <hi>moneth,</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that of the Prophet, <hi>Hosea</hi> 5.6, 7. <hi>They shall gee with their flocks to seek the Lord, but they shall not find him, he hath withdrawn himself from them; they have dealt treacherously against the Lord, for they have begotten strange children, now shall a moneth devour them with their portions;</hi> There are strange men and women Church-members this day, strange children indeed; Ile say no more of them, the wicked sing, a wonderfull <hi>and horrible thing is committed in the Land,</hi> that is, in the Church: what is that? read <hi>Jer.</hi> 5.26, to 30.</p>
                  <p>But what is the moneth here? Is it not some change think you, as the Moon doth every moneth? Sure <hi>the next change or turne of things will overturn all the Churches,</hi> for a <hi>third overturn will be:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ezek. 21.27.</note> The first was of <hi>Kingly Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative</hi> by the Parliament, then the <hi>Prelates</hi> fell; the second was of <hi>Parliamentary Priviledges,</hi> when the Army came up to purge it, then <hi>Presbyters</hi> fell: there will be a <hi>third overturn,</hi> whether for better or worse I know not, yet I hope well of the Common-wealth, and Rulers thereof, but down goe the ruling Elders with all their Churches, the very next moneth, when a change of things will be.</p>
                  <p>But thirdly, May not <hi>this moneth</hi> be another thing, yet something more?
<note place="margin">Psal. 119.96.</note> (for the <hi>Commands of God are exceeding broad,</hi> and there is a mighty bredth, height, and length in the least word of his) what is the <hi>moneth?</hi> Is it not the <hi>new Moon</hi> spoken of so much by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, as a type of that <hi>new Moon and Sabbath</hi> which shall be in the <hi>new Jerusalem,</hi> Isai. 66.22, 23.</p>
                  <p>What is the <hi>new Moon</hi> then? Truly to me it is <hi>new Light,</hi> as <hi>our life in God alone is the Sabbath</hi> there spoken: oh how terrible is this to the Pastors and Teachers to look for <hi>new light,</hi> much more to look on it, it will dazle and destroy their sight, and make them stark blind, and also dumb, as we shall see anon.</p>
                  <p>Every <hi>moneth</hi> we know the <hi>Moon</hi> receives <hi>new light</hi>
                     <pb n="52" facs="tcp:118224:29"/>as we call it, then the <hi>new Moon,</hi> though it be the old still; so the <hi>new light</hi> is nothing but the old, even the <hi>everlasting Gospel,</hi> that <hi>glory hid in God before the world,</hi> will come <hi>forth in men</hi> at last; yea, that <hi>old light of Law and Gospel-Churches,</hi> which hath been <hi>hid</hi> and darkened by the Apostacy, shall be more fully known, and come forth from all that traditionall knowledge of God which is yet received by men, <hi>Rev.</hi> 10.23.</p>
                  <p>Oh this <hi>moneth</hi> will be a <hi>day of doom</hi> to the Churches, the <hi>new Moon,</hi> this <hi>new light,</hi> will darken them at <hi>noon day;</hi> pray read <hi>Amos</hi> 8.9. where there is a greater than this yeares Eclipse, the earth is not onely darkened at noon, but <hi>the Sun goes down, and sets at high noon:</hi> What is that? When men think they are in <hi>highest light,</hi> as Churches look no higher, God doth suddenly <hi>darken them,</hi> and makes them also <hi>dumb,</hi> verse 11. for there is none left to preach the Word, being no more to be heard from North to East, verse 12. from <hi>Scotland</hi> to <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Wales.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Why is all this wrath think yee? <hi>The end is come upon my people Israel,</hi> that is the Church, verse 2. then there is the <hi>howling of the Shepheards,</hi> and their <hi>filencing,</hi> verse 3.</p>
                  <p>This is wrath indeed, but what is the cause of all? Sure first because the Churches <hi>take no care for the poor of the Land,</hi> verse 4. they may look to their own poor, but the poor of the Land <hi>are swallowed up</hi> by their si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, and made to fail, for the Ministers will not open their mouths, nor speak a good word for them to the present Governours, who doubtlesse would and will help the poor at last, though never moved by the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches.</p>
                  <p>But secondly, They cannot abide <hi>new light,</hi> therefore darknesse comes as we said, <hi>when will the new Moon be gone,</hi> say they, or as the margin reads, the <hi>new Moneth?</hi> this kills the Pastors and Teachers, this <hi>one Moneth</hi> cuts them-off by God.</p>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:118224:29"/>
                  <p> But why would they have <hi>this new Moon gone, and the Sabbath past?</hi> Oh that they may <hi>sell Corn, and set forth Wheat,</hi> verse 5. for there is no buying nor selling, nor a stitch of work to be done on the <hi>Sabbath.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Wheat, what is that? <hi>What is the Chaffe to the Wheat,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ier. 23.28.</note> saith the Prophet? Wheat sure is the <hi>pure Word,</hi> called the <hi>fat of the Kidneyes of Wheat,</hi> and so the <hi>pure word</hi> is,
<note place="margin">Deut. 32.14.</note> it is the finest fattening thing that man can take, that <hi>immortall seed of the Word, when it is sincere, spirituall, and pure,</hi> how pretious, and how powerfull it is? But <hi>what is the Chaffe to the Wheat? Chaffe</hi> hath the form and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shion of <hi>Wheat,</hi> but it goes away with the wind, yea, the <hi>Fan of the Lord,</hi> or any <hi>lufferings from men,</hi> as I said before, blowes away the Chaffe, both the Word and the Preachers of it.</p>
                  <p>But suppose <hi>it be Wheat that they sell?</hi> it is but the <hi>refuse of Wheat, as themselves confessse, Amos</hi> 8.6. what lean, low, and legall teachings doe our Preachers of the Gospel set forth and sell? it is but <hi>the refuse of all,</hi> that which good Mr. <hi>Perkins,</hi> Doctor <hi>Preston,</hi> and the rest of those pious men left behind; it is not <hi>their spirit</hi> these men speak with, it is but their words, or the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of old Writers in a new dresse.</p>
                  <p>Nay most of these Pastors or Preachers of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spel can goe no farther than the <hi>flesh of Christ,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">A chief one of the Army would once usually say, that the <hi>flesh of Christ,</hi> and <hi>letter of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture,</hi> were the two great I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dols of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christ. Iohn 6.63. Heb. 4.12.</note> and the <hi>letter of Scripture,</hi> as for that <hi>eternall Spirit</hi> which dwelt in the one, and which spake in the other, they know not; <hi>the flesh profiteth nothing,</hi> saith Christ, it is <hi>the Spirit that quickeneth, the words that I speak are Spirit and life:</hi> where is that spirituall, <hi>quick, and lively word? Spirit and life it self</hi> ministred to men, and in them?</p>
                  <p>Is it not the <hi>refuse of Wheat that they sell?</hi> when all that is sold by them is not worth the knowledge of a Christian? <hi>Henceforth,</hi> saith the Apostle, <hi>know we no man after the flesh, yea, though we have known Christ after the flesh, yet now henceforth know we him no more,</hi> 2 Cor. 5.16. We know not Christ now, saith he, but <hi>God in Christ,</hi>
                     <pb n="54" facs="tcp:118224:30"/>verse 19. for so Christ would be known, onely as the <hi>Fathers Image,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ioh, 14.9, 10.</note>
                     <hi>he that sees me sees the Father, if thou hadst known me thou wouldst have known the Father,</hi> it was God even the Father who was all in all in his flesh, <hi>who did all, and spake all, in him, and by him;</hi> he was indeed <hi>the way to the Father,</hi> not that men should <hi>stand still in Christ,</hi> as I said before, but by him <hi>goe to the Father, and with him dwell in God;</hi> so he was the <hi>truth,</hi> because the <hi>everlasting Father,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Pet. 3.18.</note>
                     <hi>the onely true God, sent the Son,</hi> or came forth in flesh, and crucified it also to himself, to <hi>bring men to God,</hi> and thus Christ was <hi>the life,</hi> and our life also.</p>
                  <p>For indeed, <hi>all the life, knowledge, and faith of a Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, by Christ as the way, doth tend and end in God,</hi> 1 Pet. 1.21. Yet this is not all, and yet this the Pastors and Teachers know not;
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 5.17.</note> for <hi>if any man be in Christ he is a new Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> or as the Greek reads, a <hi>new Creation;</hi> why, the greatest of them all goe no higher than the <hi>first Creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> as I said before.</p>
                  <p>But again, <hi>God in Christ, and Christ in men, is a Mystery yet that none of the Ministers of Churches can manifest to the world,</hi> those <hi>hidden Mysteries,</hi> and <hi>Secrets of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> that high <hi>Mystery of God even the Father, and of Christ, and the Mystery of the Gospel,</hi> these Ministers of the Gospel know not, as I shall shew (with God) ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther time.</p>
                  <p>But now see what <hi>Merchants</hi> we have in the world, mark it, <hi>they sell Wheat,</hi> nay, shame upon them, they sell <hi>the rufuse of Wheat, and sell it, for what?</hi> at the highest rate that ever was, <hi>the refuse of Wheat,</hi> an <hi>old Sermon,</hi> that is even mouldy with lying by, they will not part with without a price, yea, they sell it them at a dear rate, none will preach now under a hundered pound a year, teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is turned to a meer Trade, he that will give most shall most Gospel, under the Law all the Priests had but the like allowance, Gospel-Ministers preached freely, yet wanted nothing, now men will not trust God, but
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:118224:30"/>must have beforehand, some twenty shillings for every Sermon they make, some fortie shillings a Sermon, yea, there are Pastors and Teachers in <hi>England,</hi> who have four pound for every Sunday Sermon, besides four pound every week, for government and gaudies, or eating good cheer.</p>
                  <p>Doe not these <hi>make merchandise of the Word of God?</hi> are not these <hi>the Merchants which</hi> John <hi>speaks that shall shortly cry, alas, alas?</hi> Rev. 18.15.
<note place="margin">Rev. 18.15.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Was there ever the like heard in the world, <hi>that the refuse of wheat should be sold so dear</hi> by Divines and Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual men?</p>
                  <p>Spiritual men said I? What they who are imployed in Secular and Martiall affaires?</p>
                  <p>I doe not blame the Governours of our State, for set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting such honour and preferment on the heads of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stors and Teachers, <hi>Constantine</hi> did more, yet more mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief followed, and the <hi>Church as they say, fell asleep in</hi> Constantines <hi>lap,</hi> so I wish the wise and godly Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours of the Common-wealth to consider:</p>
                  <p>I pray consider, is it according <hi>to the order of the Gospel,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Acts 20.28.</note> that Pastors should leave their own <hi>Church-fellowships,</hi> and turn <hi>fellows of Colledges?</hi> Is it according to the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spel that Pastors should become Princes and Presidents, Deans and Doctors? Is not this a secular imployment? and this in the hands of spirituall men, is but the Instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments <hi>of a foolish Shepherd,</hi> as the Lord General <hi>Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel</hi> excellently words it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This is the great hand of God, and worthy of the conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of all those (Ministers) who taking into their hands the Instruments of a foolish Shepherd, to wit, medling with worldly policies, and mixtures of earthly power, to set up that which they call the Kingdome of Christ, which is neither it, nor if it were, would such meanes be found effectunll for that end, and neglect or not trust to the word of God, the sword of the Spirit,</hi> &amp;c. A Letter from <hi>Dumbar,</hi> p. 11.</p>
                  <p>That this is not a spiritual but a <hi>secular</hi> power, or
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:118224:31"/>
                     <hi>earthly mixture</hi> appears because an Universitie is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly the School of Nature elevated and improved by Art, not by Religious forms (though the power of it be precious) but by excellencie of learning which Pastors and Teachers are not much acquainted with, so were fitter men.</p>
                  <p>Again, It is a very sad <hi>Omen</hi> when Ministers of the Gospel, and Pastors of Churches creep so fast into Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, not onely because <hi>the prosperitie</hi> (or ease) <hi>of fools destroys them,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Prov. 1.32.</note> but it is the <hi>Geneva</hi> Note on <hi>Acts</hi> 6.12. That the first bloudie <hi>Persecution of the Church of Christ sprang up and began from a company of Priests by the sug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gestion of niversitie Doctors.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But we are gone too far from Market, we heard be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their <hi>selling the refuse of Wheat for Silver;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Amos 8.6.</note> I tell you there is more in that Verse: <hi>They buy the poor for Silver, and the needie for a pair of shooes:</hi> Or as the same Prophet speaks,
<note place="margin">Amos 2.6.</note>
                     <hi>They sell the righteous for silver, and the poor for a pair of shooes.</hi> That is, if there be a righteous poor man that seeks the publike good <hi>of the Common-wealth,</hi> or the <hi>good of mankind,</hi> they will either keep him poor, or make him rich, they will stop his mouth with a <hi>piece of silver,</hi> or send him away in a <hi>pair of shooes.</hi> Whats that? set him in a <hi>good office,</hi> or <hi>gainfull imployment,</hi> thats <hi>a pair of shooes</hi> that many an honest heart is bought and sold for.</p>
                  <p>I wonder that the Prophet should say of God, <hi>Thou hast forsaken thy people the house of Jacob,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Isai. 2.7.</note> &amp;c. <hi>Why? Their land is full of silver and gold, and there is no end of their trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Truly it were well the tidings had bin true, That we Christians would have no more silver and gold from the <hi>Indies,</hi> then gold should not be our God: But now I fear me that <hi>Mammon</hi> is not onely the <hi>god</hi> of the world, but the god of Churches also, yea many good Christians make Mammon and money their God.</p>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:118224:31"/>
                  <p> In the Apostles dayes, <hi>The love of money was the root of all evill,</hi> it lay close in the Earth, but now it is <hi>risen to a Tree</hi> all men may see that money is most loved by good and bad alike.
<note place="margin">Ezek. 7.10.11</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Paul</hi> speaks of a <hi>cloaked covetousnesse,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Thes. 2.5.</note> it was much co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered and kept close then, because indeed the Churches were so pure and poor, but now covetousnesse walks a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad by day without any cloak stark naked, that all doe see and cry shame on the Saints this day?</p>
                  <p>Oh the <hi>hour of Temptation is come upon all them that dwell on the earth;</hi> True, that <hi>dwell on the earth;</hi> yea,
<note place="margin">Rev. 3.10.</note> those who <hi>dwell in heaven</hi> are tempted with it also, the glory of the <hi>world was the last and greatest of all Christs Temptations,</hi> Matth. 4.8.</p>
                  <p>I doe not envie your greatnesse (God knows) but pitty your goodness that is so besieged with great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness and Worldly glory, with Silver, and Gold,
<note place="margin">Psal. 73.7.</note> and Money, and more then <hi>heart could wish,</hi> the Lords and Nobles of old could doe better with it because Gentlemen born, but when so much money comes into the hands of poor Saints, oh, how they hold it, and hug it, and hunger after more, as dogs after dry bones. Woe, woe to the Churches, and Christians this day. Truly Friend, I was forced as first to speak, then to write, so now to publish these things to the world.</p>
                  <p>I would much rather have been at home, and sate in silence, yea better had it been for my flesh and family, if I had (as I said) even enter <hi>into my chambers,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Isai. 26.20.</note>
                     <hi>and shut the door upon me untill the Indignation bee overpast,</hi> that is, till all the seven Vials full of wrath be poured forth; there is wrath enough on the Churches already, their own divisions would destroy them quick enough; and why then must I come forth like a fool, and put my head between their blows.</p>
                  <p>But yet God hath appointed a worm to pour out wrath on the Churches, to pour out wrath, and yet in love, to lye under the same wrath with them, and for
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:118224:32"/>their sake to suffer this, for he that kills with the <hi>sword, shall be killed by the sword,</hi> Rev. 13.10. 'Tis not my hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piness then, but <hi>Woe is me my mother, that thou hast made me a man of contention to all the earth,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ier. 15.10.</note> &amp;c. First, to Prelates, then to Presbyters, now to Independent Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stors and Teachers; It is my <hi>mother the Church</hi> hath made me thus, for my Fathers Spirit, the promise of the Father in me doth teach me better things.</p>
                  <p>There are better things indeed that the Saints should wait for, things above Law and Gospel-order, if it were as it was,
<note place="margin">Ier. 50.45.</note> but is not, things which neither Prophets, nor Apostles attained to, yet both did write of, and wait for,
<note place="margin">Rom. 8.21.</note>
                     <hi>the glory to be revealed in us,</hi> the <hi>glorious libertie of the sons of God,</hi> and of the sons of men also, even of the <hi>whole Creation;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 Pet. 3.13.</note> the <hi>new Heaven</hi> and <hi>new Earth,</hi> the <hi>new Jerusalem,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Ioh. 3.2.</note> the <hi>appearance</hi> of the great God in us, when <hi>we shall be like him, and see him as he is, see his face, and his name on our foreheads,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rev. 22.1, 2, 3, 4, &amp;c.</note> when there shall be <hi>no curse, nor cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, nor death;</hi> but the <hi>tree of life</hi> in the midst of us, the River of <hi>life, cleer as Crystall</hi> proceeding out of the Throne of God and the Lamb that is in us: These are the <hi>living waters,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Zach. 14.8. Job 20.17. Ioel 3.18.</note> the Rivers and Brooks of <hi>butter and honey</hi> the Prophets speak of, yea, the <hi>mountains dropping down new wine, and the hills flowing with milk</hi> is more then was in Gospel-times,
<note place="margin">Acts 2.</note> the <hi>new wine,</hi> the Spirit which the Apostles were drunk with at first, was but the <hi>first fruits,</hi> but a taste of that which shall be more fully drawn forth in the last dayes,
<note place="margin">Zach. 9.15. Rev. 19.6.</note> when men <hi>shall drink and make a noise as through wine, and be filled with bowls,</hi> &amp;c. yea, make a noise <hi>as of thunder, being the voice of much people in heaven,</hi> and of many Allelujahs. Those who shall sing and speak really and indeed these <hi>glad tidings to men</hi> shall not want <hi>money</hi> nor <hi>meanes,</hi> for <hi>City and Country</hi> (and <hi>Kings</hi> too) shall contribute their <hi>glory to them,</hi> the <hi>City Merchant</hi> shall give them food and raiment, <hi>Isai.</hi> 23.18. and Country Farmers shall serve their wives and children to plow sow, and reap for them, <hi>Isai.</hi> 61.4, 5, 6, and 9. verses, yea,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:118224:32"/>the Lord God himself will be ready as a servant,
<note place="margin">Isai. 45.11. Isai. 58.9.</note> to wait <hi>on them at their command, and at their call (Here am I,</hi> saith he) <hi>to those who undoe the heavie burthens, and let the oppressed goe free, and break every yoke</hi> (from mens states and spirits) this the everlasting Gospel will doe, <hi>Isai.</hi> 58.6, 7, 8, 9, 12. verses compared.</p>
                  <p>This is also the <hi>Sabbath</hi> before spoken of (which the Ministers there wish it were over) not onely to <hi>cease from our own works,</hi> but from speaking our <hi>own words,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Heb. 4.10. Isai. 58.13.</note> or from <hi>speaking words</hi> as the Hebrew reads, <hi>v.</hi> 13.
<note place="margin">Heb. 22.19.</note> The Law in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed was <hi>a voice of words,</hi> and the preaching of the Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel at first, was in this far below its own light, at least below that glory of the <hi>everlasting Gospel</hi> at last, which shall not be in <hi>words</hi> or speakings,
<note place="margin">Rev. 19.8. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc> in non-Latin alphabet </desc>
                        </gap>.</note> but in the righteous actings of men, the <hi>righteousnesses of Saints,</hi> Rev. 19.8. The <hi>Angel</hi> who is to preach the <hi>everlasting Gospel,</hi> is no particular man, or men (as in the <hi>Gospel-Ministry</hi> at first) but the Spirit it self, even the <hi>glorious appearance of the great God</hi> in Men, and in Magistrates first shall Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister that <hi>light and love and glory to bee revealed</hi> in us. Thus the <hi>Angel flyes in the midst of heaven,</hi> &amp;c. Rev. 14.6. the other Angel <hi>v.</hi> 7. is another appearance of God in men.
<note place="margin">Revel. 21.24.</note> For as the <hi>Kings of the Earth bring their glory</hi> and honour <hi>to the New Jerusalem,</hi> (that of the <hi>New Jerusalem</hi> being the sum of the everlasting Gospel) so these <hi>Kings of the earth</hi> who shall be, are the <hi>ten Kings who burn the whores flesh with fire,</hi> Rev. 17.16.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>ten Kings</hi> are not a Kingly power, for Monarchy will never burn Ministery, (the whores flesh) but such a government of men, <hi>who have received no Kingdome as yet, but receive power as Kings one hour with the Beast, Rev.</hi> 17.12. as the two Beasts are false Ministery under severall forms, so the Beast here is the second Beast, (
<note n="*" place="margin">The Beast and the <hi>false Prophet were taken,</hi> &amp;c. The Beast is the first Beast, the false Prophet is the second Beast <hi>who did Miracles.</hi>
                     </note> called the false Prophet, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.20.) who hath two <hi>hornes like a lambe,</hi> this being the purest Ministerie, and most like <hi>Christ,</hi> though indeed of Antichrist, <hi>doing and speaking as the Dragon and first Beast did,</hi> Rev. 23.11, 12.</p>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:118224:33"/>
                  <p> To this second Beast the <hi>ten Kings with one mind give their power and strength,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rev. 13.14. Rev. 19.20. compared.</note>
                     <hi>and make war with the Lamb,</hi> oppose and persecute the high appearance of God in his <hi>suffering Saints,</hi> who are said to be <hi>with him, who</hi> also <hi>by suffering shall overcome</hi> at last, both the <hi>Beast and ten Kings</hi> with him, <hi>Rev,</hi> 17.13, 14. compared with <hi>Revel.</hi> 12.11.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>ten Kings</hi> being thus <hi>overcome</hi> by the Spirit of the Lord in his people (and by the same Spirit appearing in themselves) shall hate <hi>the whore</hi> (with the Beast) and <hi>shall burn her flesh with fire,</hi> Rev. 17.16.</p>
                  <p>But before this (as I said) they had <hi>given their power to the Beast,</hi> the reason why they gave it is strange, and should still all the murmurings of men: <hi>For God put it in their hearts to fulfill his will; and to agree, and to give their Kingdom to the Beast, untill the words of God shall be ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled,</hi> Rev. 17.17.</p>
                  <p>When the words of God are fulfilled, then the <hi>woman</hi> (that <hi>whorish spirit</hi> or dependance on Men and Ministers which reigns <hi>over the Kings of the earth</hi>) the ten <hi>Kings shall burn with fire,</hi> that is, by the power and Spirit of the Lord God appearing in them as <hi>Fire.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>These ten Kings then seem to me to be a <hi>State Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> (like ours) who have no <hi>Kingdom as yet</hi> (not yet setled) though the Beast may make them believe <hi>they are Kings for an hour,</hi> for that little time of the Beasts reign over them, but the <hi>Kings can doe nothing,</hi> they can doe no more nor longer, then the <hi>Lord puts in their hearts,</hi> as was said before, therefore when the <hi>Word of God is ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled,</hi> and his time accomplished, The <hi>ten Kings</hi> (though formerly ruled by <hi>the Beast,</hi> and loving <hi>the whore,</hi> yet now) <hi>hate her, make her desolate, and naked, eat her flesh, and burn her with fire,</hi> Rev. 17.16, 17.</p>
                  <p>[How beloved were the Bishops or Prelates to most of the <hi>present powers,</hi> in whom yet such a Spirit since appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that hath burnt up all those, and will them that follow.]</p>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:118224:33"/>
                  <p> Those <hi>Kings then who bring their glory and honour to the new Jerusalem,</hi> are the <hi>ten Kings,</hi> and these <hi>ten Kings</hi> are the Christian Magistrates (it may be ours) for as the <hi>Nations of them that are saved</hi> are joyned with them, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.24. so these <hi>three Nations</hi> I beleeve will be the first <hi>saved ones</hi> in the world, from Monarchy, and Tyranny, and <hi>Babylons</hi> captivity, from all Oppression and Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage on mens States and Spirits.</p>
                  <p>The summe of all is this, That the Appearance of God in the Christian Magistrate also, will goe forth as the flying Angel, &amp;c. 2. That fire whereby they burn the Whores flesh; is the Spirit of the Lord God in them. 3. That Spirit which appeared in the Ministers of Christ preaching the Gospel at first, will now appear in the Christian Magistrate much more at last. 4. As the <hi>Magistrate</hi> is the <hi>Minister of God,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rom. 13.4.</note> and the onely true Minister now (there being none in the Church) so God in the last dayes will first appear with power and glory, not in the Church, but in the Common-wealth, not in Ministers at all, but in the Magistrate both Civill and Martiall.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Lord will save the Tents of Judah first,</hi> Zach. 12.7. And <hi>the Governours of Judah shall say in their hearts, the</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>The Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>salem</hi> are those who have the high discove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of God dwelling in them, these are the strength of the State, the <hi>Chariots and Horsemen of Israel,</hi> as the Generall speaks anon.</note>
                     <hi>Inhabitants of Jerusalem shall be my strength in the Lord their God,</hi> verse 5. Again, <hi>I will make thine Officers peace, and thine Exactors righteousnesse, &amp;c.</hi> Isai. 60.17, 18.</p>
                  <p>Indeed if any man doth but observe and follow the foot-steps of the Almighty this day, in his wayes and wonders among men, his glorious Appearance, and his Power, and Goodnesse in this Land hath been most visible to, and by the Magistrate Civill and Martiall, at home and abroad, both by land and sea, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Alas, what have the Ministers done, but undone themselves and others? and still like to undoe the whole Nation, as the Prelates in the first warre, the Presbyters in the second warre, and though a third warre will not be, yet the prosperity, peace, and happy proceedings
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:118224:34"/>of the present Powers, how had the Independent and Baptized Churches like to hinder? how saucy and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solent were they about a new Representative? yea, no Parliament men, but Church-members, or chosen by them, was once in print: it is more observable, those Churches who could never communicate, nor come to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether before, became as one Congregation, to divide and undoe the Common-wealth if possibly they could.</p>
                  <p>Well said noble Generall again. <hi>We pray you own his people more and more, for they are the Chariots and Horsemen of Israel, disown your selves, but own your authority and power to curb the proud and the insolent, such as would disturb the tranquility of</hi> England, <hi>under what specious pretences soever; releive the oppressed, hear the groanes of the Priso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners in</hi> England (when Lord God holy and true, and a Treasury for the poor?) <hi>Be pleased to reform the abuses of all Professions, and if there be any one that makes many poor to make a few rich, that suits not a Common-wealth:</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Heu quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum est in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus inane?</hi> that is, A thing well said, then done, when power is in thine hand, Would blesse thy soul, wife, children, and the land.</note> very well said indeed. The Lord Generall <hi>Cromwels</hi> Letter from <hi>Dumbar,</hi> pag. 10.</p>
                  <p>How many <hi>men are made poor,</hi> by making a few <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters rich?</hi> therefore there is but little good done by the <hi>greatest Ministers</hi> this day in <hi>England and Ireland;</hi> their whole work is in calling men to <hi>Church, not to Christ,</hi> in converting <hi>Saints, not Sinners:</hi> alas man, it is not the <hi>Gospel,</hi> but thine own <hi>gain</hi> thou most lookest after.</p>
                  <p>That which you hear of so many <hi>called in Wales,</hi> is not so true as the report, it is but <hi>to Church</hi> that multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes run, and most to <hi>the waters,</hi> but alas poor soules, they are still as simple and earthly as ever they were, as ignorant, carnall, and covetous, as little power of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linesse, or knowledge in the Mystery of Christ, self-de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyall, sincerity, and singlenesse of heart: oh they are more double and divided, that light and love which was formerly in <hi>Wales</hi> in good Mr. <hi>Wroth</hi>'s dayes, is dead with him, and quite darkened.</p>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:118224:34"/>
                  <p> When will the Lord take away the <hi>reproach of his people</hi> from off all the earth? <hi>Isaiah</hi> 25.8.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>They know not to doe right, saith the Lord, who store up violence and robbery in their Palaces,</hi> Amos 3.10.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Are yee not as children of</hi> Aethiopians <hi>unto me, oh yee children of Israel?</hi> Amos 9.7, 10.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He is Canaan</hi> (saith the margin) <hi>or a Merchant, the balliances of deceit are in his hand, he loveth to oppresse,</hi> Hos. 12.7.</p>
                  <p>What <hi>Merchants</hi> the <hi>Ministers</hi> are of the <hi>Word</hi> we have heard before, and what <hi>Merchandize Church-mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers</hi> make of the <hi>World,</hi> the world will see very shortly.</p>
                  <p>Truly in all that I have said,
<note place="margin">Psal. 37.15.</note> I doe not <hi>condemn the generation of the Righteous,</hi> but the <hi>generations of Vipers,</hi> who under <hi>formes of Religion</hi> eat up their Mothers bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els, even the <hi>power of Righteousnesse,</hi> the <hi>Church of the first-born,</hi> yea, <hi>Jerusalem that is above, which is free, and the Mother of us all coming down from God out of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> these men and Ministers would hinder and hide in <hi>the Earth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Again, I doe not judge the <hi>Governours of our State,</hi> nor <hi>State Ministers,</hi> sent forth by the <hi>power of man,</hi> to civilize and teach the people, to instruct the Nation in <hi>peace and holinesse,</hi> and in
<note n="*" place="margin">There be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing now no <hi>Ministers of the Gospel</hi> who can goe forth <hi>freely</hi> to the world <hi>with power from on high; State Ministers</hi> will never doe good till they <hi>gain the hearts of the people to the present Powers,</hi> in whom God hath so visibly appeared, that men cannot chuse but see and be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced; that there is yet <hi>more good to be done by them, and for us,</hi> in Gods due time.</note>
                     <hi>honourable thoughts of the present Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> which (though yet <hi>clouded under particular cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions, and crooching under its own greatnesse</hi>) will ride on prosperoufly through the three Nations, and rise a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all the Nations round about, in spight of all their threats or attempts, yea, (though there may be a black moneth) yet the glory of the Lord shall cover it, till the <hi>glorious liberty of the Sonnes of God</hi> (and of Men also) shall arise as the Sun in this <hi>Land</hi> at last, as the first fruits of freedome, and healing to the world, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.24. <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.2. compared.</p>
                  <p>Lastly, Let no <hi>Independent Pastor, nor Presbyters,</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessing themselves <hi>Ministers of the Gospel,</hi> dare to meddle any more with <hi>Tithes,</hi> forced <hi>Contributions,</hi> or <hi>Consolida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi>
                     <pb n="64" facs="tcp:118224:35"/>nor make a <hi>gain of Godlinesse,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Tim. 6.5. 1 Tim. 3.3. Iude 11.</note> nor a <hi>Trade of Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> because the <hi>Servant that knowes his Masters will</hi> and doth it not, shall be <hi>beaten with many stripes, Luke</hi> 12, 47. that is, the Lord Christ will <hi>strip you,</hi> and <hi>whip you</hi> round about the Country.</p>
                  <p>Surely <hi>I come quickly, Amen, even so come Lord Jesus,</hi> oh how <hi>suddenly</hi> is he <hi>come to his Temple?</hi> truly brethren the Lord is come, and now making a <hi>Scourge of</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">The least Christians shall scourge the greatest Churches. Ier. 50.45. Iohn 2.15.</note>
                     <hi>small cords, to drive the money changers out of the Temple.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The vile person shall be no more called liberall, nor the churle said to be bountifull.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But the vile person shall speak vilanny, and his heart will work iniquity, to practise hypocrisie, and to utter error against the Lord, to make empty the soul of the hungry, and he will cause the drink of the thirsty to fail.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The instruments also of the churle are evill, he deviseth wicked devises to destroy the poor with lying words, even when the needy speaketh right.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But the liberall deviseth liberall things, and by liberall things shall he stand,</hi> Isaiah 32.5, 6, 7, 8.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:118224:35"/>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>